<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Israel's troubles and triumph, or, The history of their dangers in and deliverance out of Egypt as it is recorded by Moses in Exod. and turned into English verse by George Lesly.</title>
            <author>Lesly, George, d. 1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11725171</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11725171</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47781)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1486:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Israel's troubles and triumph, or, The history of their dangers in and deliverance out of Egypt as it is recorded by Moses in Exod. and turned into English verse by George Lesly.</title>
                  <author>Lesly, George, d. 1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and sold by Nicholas Woolf ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [4]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Exodus --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
               <term>Bible stories, English --  O.T. Exodus.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48379:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48379:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s TROUBLES AND TRIUMPH. OR, The Hiſtory of
their dangers in, and deliverance out of <hi>EGYPT.</hi> AS It is recorded by
<hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Exod.</hi> AND Turned into <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Verſe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE LESLY,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of <hi>Olney.
Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Diſcite Juſtitiam Moniti</l>
               <bibl>Virg.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Hearken to a Verſer, who may chance</l>
               <l>Rhime thee to good, and make a bait of
pleaſure.</l>
               <bibl>Herbert</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and ſold by
<hi>Nicholas Woolf,</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>Star Court, Cheapſide.</hi>
1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48379:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48379:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Author makes no apology for what he hath here offered, being
fully perſwaded, that he hath injured no man; but in the<pb facs="tcp:48379:3"/>room of
that, or a prolix Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, he deſires me to inform you (if you be
ſtrangers in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and know not) that ſince the loweſt
of the people daily invade the Miniſterial Office, he thinks that for
harmleſs humour, and innocent diverſion, an ancient Preacher may turn
Religious Poet; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Rhimes (as he ſaith) were of old the common
Theology, and why they may not be ſubſervient to it yet he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not.
However, taking it for granted, he was reſolved, with the Great Apoſtle, to
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all things to all men,<pb facs="tcp:48379:3"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any true Son of
the Muſes ſeem to be diſſatisfied, he ſaith to ſuch (as
<hi>Gideon</hi> did to the angry <hi>Ephramites</hi>) what have I done now in
compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of you? Is not the glean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Grapes of <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
better than the Vintage of <hi>Abie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:48379:4"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 19. r. <hi>them:</hi> p. 13. l. 13. r.
<hi>Iſacides:</hi> p. 18. l. 20. r. <hi>Sire:</hi> l. 30. r. <hi>your:</hi>
p. 19. l. 24. r. <hi>your:</hi> p. 20. l. 23. r. <hi>armies:</hi> p. 21. l. 10.
r. <hi>Sire:</hi> p. 26. l. 20. leave out <hi>A grant:</hi> p. 36. l. 7. r.
<hi>hear:</hi> p. 38. l. 7. r. <hi>thoſe:</hi> p. 39. l. 3. r. <hi>yet:</hi>
p. 44. l. 1. r. <hi>Sun:</hi> p. 51. l. 10. r. <hi>Remote:</hi> p. 55. l. 12.
r. <hi>were:</hi> p. 36. l. 31. r. <hi>delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> p. 61. l. 3. add
<hi>great:</hi> l. 6. dele <hi>their:</hi> p. 63. l. 17. r. <hi>God:</hi> p.
69. l. 8. r. <hi>ro:</hi> p. 72. l. 19. r. <hi>deſcrie:</hi> p. 75. l. 25. r.
<hi>dear:</hi> p. 78. l. 7. r. <hi>May:</hi> l. 26. add <hi>himſelf:</hi> p.
81. l. 7. r. <hi>never:</hi> p. 85. l. 28. r. <hi>not:</hi> p. 87. l. 11. add
<hi>then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and what others are not taken notice of, the Reader is
requeſted to do it as he reads.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48379:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s TROUBLES AND TRIUMPH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Sing th' Almighty's Friend and <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s guide,</l>
               <l>His birth and reſcue from th' impetuous tide</l>
               <l>Of rapid <hi>Nile,</hi> I ſing his Mother's care:</l>
               <l>His Royal Nurſe; and how Heav'n's mercies are.</l>
               <l>Like himſelf boundleſs; his own acts I ſing,</l>
               <l>Whoſe growing greatneſs, griev'd the grumbling King,</l>
               <l>And all his Subjects: who combin'd to have</l>
               <l>His guiltleſs blood; how he was forc'd to leave</l>
               <l>A Princely Court: where ev'ry thing lookt brave;</l>
               <l>His wand'rings, and his happy Reſidence</l>
               <l>At laſt, with <hi>Jethro, Midian</hi> Prieſt, and
Prince,</l>
               <l>His Nuptials, Trade, and of the great content</l>
               <l>He had in hours on Mathematicks ſpent,</l>
               <l>Aſtronomy was pleaſant, but Gods Law</l>
               <l>Delighted moſt: ſince by its light he ſaw</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48379:5"/>His change of State, his en'mies pride and fall,</l>
               <l>He ſaw himſelf made Heav'n's General,</l>
               <l>The flaming Buſh and Voice confirmed all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Province, Lord, a greater light requires</l>
               <l>Than can be kindled by <hi>Promethean</hi> fires.</l>
               <l>The way's unbeaten, ſlipp'ry, dark and ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Conduct thy Servant, that he may not range</l>
               <l>Too high 'bove what is written, nor too low,</l>
               <l>It's truth, not fancy, I deſire to ſhow;</l>
               <l>Truth, to convince the world of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s ſins</l>
               <l>And puniſhments, with thee my Muſe begins.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the great, the good, the juſt and
wiſe,</l>
               <l>Remov'd from <hi>Memphis</hi> unto Paradice,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to that fair <hi>Elizian</hi> grove,</l>
               <l>To perfect and perpetuate their love:</l>
               <l>Left <hi>Iſrael</hi> bleſt with all the happineſs</l>
               <l>Their King and Brother could by deeds expreſs:</l>
               <l>Which they in peace profound for many years</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt, ne're harb'ring jealouſies nor fears,</l>
               <l>Admir'd, careſs'd, and lov'd by ev'ry one,</l>
               <l>From the rude Cottage, to the Royal Throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But (ah!) where time is nam'd, there's nothing ſure,</l>
               <l>All have Convulſions, Cramps, or Calenture;</l>
               <l>Earth hath ſtrong Palſies that do ſhake its frame;</l>
               <l>Man accidents, ten thouſand without name,</l>
               <l>Sent from the Throne Celeſtial, or Abyſs,</l>
               <l>To ſhew how vain a thing is humane bliſs.</l>
               <l>Their day's o'recaſt, and ſtormy Clouds appear,</l>
               <l>When a ſtrange heir ſat in th' Imperial Chair:</l>
               <l>Whoſe haughty humour taught him to deſpiſe</l>
               <l>His Predeceſſors Laws, tho Juſt and Wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48379:5"/>
               <l>Our Gods themſelves, count it a ſaucy thing,</l>
               <l>Said he, in Vaſſals to adviſe their King.</l>
               <l>A Monarchy that's abſolute I'll have,</l>
               <l>I'll change the name of Subject into Slave.</l>
               <l>To reign one day is much more glorious</l>
               <l>Without controul: than ages curbed thus</l>
               <l>With endleſs Counſels. I will
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e alone;</l>
               <l>By borrow'd light the former <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſhone;</l>
               <l>I muſt Eclipſe that. Turning to his Court,</l>
               <l>You ſee, ſaid he, the great, the oft reſort</l>
               <l>Of all ſorts daily to our <hi>Goſhenites,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This chills my blood, this checks my active ſp'rits.</l>
               <l>Ah me, oppreſt! My thoughts I can't relate,</l>
               <l>My apprehenſions of our falling ſtate</l>
               <l>Are black and diſmal, my night dreams foretel</l>
               <l>Our overthrow by them that with us dwell.</l>
               <l>And here he ſtopt: tho more he would have ſaid,</l>
               <l>Leaving the reſt to tears, which crav'd their aid:</l>
               <l>Tears! that like torrents from his eyes diſtill'd,</l>
               <l>All the beholders with amazement fill'd,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſympathizing eyes and hearts condole,</l>
               <l>The tort'ring torments of his troubled ſoul,</l>
               <l>With pickled ſighs; which o're, they bow and ſay,</l>
               <l>Dread Soveraign, do you propoſe the way,</l>
               <l>Your ſorrow's ours: if that be its true riſe,</l>
               <l>The common Foe at once well ſacrifice;</l>
               <l>Which is ſoon done, if we right meaſures take,</l>
               <l>That's vent'ring all for King and Country's ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This brisk reſolve reviv'd the drooping King,</l>
               <l>So as the aged Winter's by the Spring;</l>
               <l>His center'd blood reſum'd its circ'lar courſe,</l>
               <l>The briny ſtreams are ſtopped at their ſource;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48379:6"/>All parts are changed, clarify'd his eyes,</l>
               <l>His tongue's unty'd, with which he magnifies</l>
               <l>Their Love and Courage. Daring ſouls, ſaid he,</l>
               <l>This undertaking calls for ſecrecy,</l>
               <l>Since they we muſt attack moſt ſubtile be.</l>
               <l>If it takes air, they'll quickly trace the ſcent,</l>
               <l>Deſtroy our Perſons and our Government.</l>
               <l>Once more invade; then we muſt bow the head</l>
               <l>(As heretofore) with pray'rs and tears for bread:</l>
               <l>Or if a Foreign Foe ſhould us infeſt,</l>
               <l>They'd joyn with them, and prove worſe than the reſt.</l>
               <l>They know our Strength, they know our Houſes well,</l>
               <l>They know our Cloſets, where we Money tell:</l>
               <l>Which they would rifle, and from us be gone,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt this I know no Remedy but one,</l>
               <l>(They live in wealth and eaſe, as if their Land</l>
               <l>Was not by Grace, but by a conqu'ring hand.</l>
               <l>This irritates their wild and wealthy Souls,</l>
               <l>To publiſh <hi>Iſrael</hi> wiſe, and us kind Fools.)</l>
               <l>I muſt an Edict frame, that may ſuppreſs</l>
               <l>Their pride and pow'r, and all our wrongs redreſs;</l>
               <l>Which muſt run thus. Our Countries open'lye,</l>
               <l>To ev'ry one that hath a wiſhing eye,</l>
               <l>On us ſuch may make Inroads when they pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Deſtroy our State, our Fruits, diſturb our eaſe,</l>
               <l>And ſtop our Traffick both by Land and Seas.</l>
               <l>In ev'ry Town I'll raiſe a Cittadel,</l>
               <l>That Foreign Force I may with Force repel,</l>
               <l>And keep theſe under, leſt they ſhould rebel.</l>
               <l>Then for Proviſions, Store houſes I'll build</l>
               <l>To theſe: for their own ſafety they will yield.</l>
               <l>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h raviſh'd ears
th' <hi>Egyptians</hi> heard this thing,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, what Nation e're had ſuch a King.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48379:6"/>He's wiſe as <hi>Phoebus,</hi> valiant, yet
kind,</l>
               <l>This ſeeming favour will the <hi>Hebrews</hi> bind</l>
               <l>To own this new deſign, and to employ</l>
               <l>Themſelves in it, tho it themſelves deſtroy,</l>
               <l>Make them our ſlaves, and us their wealth enjoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Loyalty ſhuts its eyes to ev'ry thing,</l>
               <l>'That may its King into ſuſpicion bring,</l>
               <l>'And theirs is ſuch, (for any thing we know)</l>
               <l>'A God above they own, but you below,</l>
               <l>'Confirm it, Sir—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This black deſign is now ſo cloſely laid</l>
               <l>That no eye ſaw't, nor ear heard what they ſaid,</l>
               <l>But Hell's and theirs, thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> was betray'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Rage, Malice, Fury, Blood, Revenge, till now,</l>
               <l>'Ne're ſeiz'd the heart, nor ſat upon the brow</l>
               <l>'Of any former <hi>Pharoah,</hi> Meekneſs, Love,</l>
               <l>'Adorn'd their Temples, bleſſings from above.</l>
               <l>'Bleſt Souls ſuch virtues made, their Kingdom great</l>
               <l>'Then lov'd by Friends, their Foes for peace to treat,</l>
               <l>'And of their plenty Foreigners did eat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Conference into a Law is paſt,</l>
               <l>And Proclamations iſſu'd out in haſte</l>
               <l>Through all the Tribes, to let them underſtand</l>
               <l>That none muſt be Free-holders in that Land.</l>
               <l>All muſt do ſuit and ſervice, pay quit-rent,</l>
               <l>Or elſe be forced into baniſhment.</l>
               <l>This our juſt Law, if any doth deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Him we to our Revenge will ſacrifice.</l>
               <l>There's no appeal, I'm abſolute you know,</l>
               <l>I kill and ſave, my Subjects all muſt bow</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48379:7"/>At my ſole beck—Your anſwers quickly
give,</l>
               <l>Obedience is the only way to live,</l>
               <l>If I condemn, there's none can you reprieve.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With fault'ring tongues, faint hearts, the Tribes reply,</l>
               <l>(It is well known) we never did deny</l>
               <l>Our King's commands, we do not think it ſtrange</l>
               <l>To ſee new Monarchs make in Laws a change.</l>
               <l>We will obey, we know ſubmiſſion's due</l>
               <l>Firſt to our Fathers God, and then to you.</l>
               <l>What muſt we do—Some thouſands you muſt take,</l>
               <l>Who for defence of us and you muſt make</l>
               <l>Brick for our buildings, and what elſe we lack.</l>
               <l>Our winged haſte admits of no delay,</l>
               <l>The act (you know) commenc'd this very day,</l>
               <l>That ſome of them make Brick, ſome overſee</l>
               <l>The reſt, and give a juſt account when we</l>
               <l>The ſame require—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'When peremptory Acts come from the State</l>
               <l>'There is no time giv'n to deliberate</l>
               <l>'On what is right, if not, none muſt debate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Labourers are choſen by the beſt,</l>
               <l>Who with ſmooth words encourage all the reſt:</l>
               <l>Fear nothing, Sirs, this ſudden ſtorm will o're,</l>
               <l>And we enjoy our Freedom as before.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, th' <hi>Egyptian</hi> Task-maſters appear,</l>
               <l>Whoſe furious frowns gave them juſt cauſe to fear</l>
               <l>'Twas otherwiſe. Come, Sparks, where are, your Tools?</l>
               <l>See! how they gaze, and ſtare, they think we're Fools.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48379:7"/>Take you this Spade, and you that Pickaxe take,</l>
               <l>Bind you that Leather Budget to your back.</l>
               <l>What elſe is wanting? Here, take up this Trowel:</l>
               <l>The day comes on. All whiſper, this is cruel.</l>
               <l>Thus rigg'd, they travel to the Slimy Pits,</l>
               <l>Where ſome are dampt with fumes, ſome had ſtrong fits,</l>
               <l>Some choak'd in mud, others with cold are kill'd,</l>
               <l>Moſt ſwoon with fear, the reſt with Sorrow fill'd,</l>
               <l>Cry out, Alas! now, now we ſee (tho late)</l>
               <l>Approaching ruin—</l>
               <l>Haſte, haſte away, you ſee it is in vain</l>
               <l>To fret and murmur, or of us complain,</l>
               <l>It is decreed, and we your Guides expect</l>
               <l>That you ſhall always act as we direct.</l>
               <l>If you incenſe your Monarch, or our wrath,</l>
               <l>Your puniſhment will be a ling'ring death.</l>
               <l>Compliance is the only way to pleaſe</l>
               <l>Both him and us—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'He that can form th' Idea of a fair,</l>
               <l>'A glorious Princeſs in a Royal Chair,</l>
               <l>'Adorn'd with all the wonders of the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>'Whoſe common fare is not a common feaſt;</l>
               <l>'One, whoſe Attendants could exceed the train</l>
               <l>'Of <hi>Philip</hi>'s Son, or that of <hi>Charlemaign,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Caſt down from honours top to dark diſgrace,</l>
               <l>'Amongſt the baſer ſort of Human Race,</l>
               <l>'Wrapt up in Rags, black, wrinkled, and half dead,</l>
               <l>'May in her Face poor <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Fortune read,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such was their grief, and ſuch their mis'ries were,</l>
               <l>Hard was their work, and harder much their fare:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48379:8"/>Yet had they ſtill a numerous
Off-ſpring,</l>
               <l>Which gave new wounds to the freſh-bleeding King.</l>
               <l>Where ſhall I turn, ſaid he? where ſhall I go?</l>
               <l>The more I ſeek their fall, the more they grow.</l>
               <l>Speak boldly, brave <hi>Egyptians,</hi> let your breath</l>
               <l>Condemn them, let your Swords give preſent death</l>
               <l>To all their Males: This will appeaſe my wrath.</l>
               <l>If Infant blood can cure your hearts diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Their Infants all ſhall bleed to give you eaſe:</l>
               <l>We are agreed, that <hi>Nile</hi>'s deep watry Tomb,</l>
               <l>Shall ſwallow up their Children from the Womb,</l>
               <l>There ev'ry Male as ſoon as born ſhall lye;</l>
               <l>Which will in time deſtroy their progeny,</l>
               <l>Defeat their Counſels, Plots and Policies,</l>
               <l>Compleat our Joys, compleat their Miſeries,</l>
               <l>For in the Childrens murders Parents dye,</l>
               <l>They only live to ſing their obſequy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Bravely reſolv'd! but who can do a thing</l>
               <l>So cruel? Heav'n and Earth of us will ring,</l>
               <l>To our eternal ſhame if we miſcarry,</l>
               <l>He that's moſt Loyal, ought to be moſt wary.</l>
               <l>Fear nothing, Sir, this project will ſucceed</l>
               <l>As you deſire, our Midwives are agreed</l>
               <l>Joyntly, as one to act as we command—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They're merciful, and dare not lift a hand</l>
               <l>Againſt a Gaſping Infant: but will ſave</l>
               <l>Not kill, nor drown them in that Liquid Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Let Tyrants thirſt for blood, and meaſures take</l>
               <l>'Againſt Heav'ns will, ſuch meaſures he will break,</l>
               <l>'No Weapon form'd againſt his Friends can prove</l>
               <l>'Deadly, for they are ſhielded with his love.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48379:8"/>This pious act ſoon ſounds in
<hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s ears,</l>
               <l>Bringing new woes, new jealouſies, new fears;</l>
               <l>To which he giveth vent by Sighs and Tears.</l>
               <l>Did I not foreſee what the Queans would do,</l>
               <l>Tho they Commiſſion had from me and you,</l>
               <l>(They who State ſecrets do commit to Women,</l>
               <l>Deſerve to loſe their honour, and turn Yeomen)</l>
               <l>'Tis manifeſt, you did with them combine</l>
               <l>To croſs my lawful, croſs my juſt deſign;</l>
               <l>Call in the Strumpets, they muſt ſhow the cauſe</l>
               <l>Of their contempt of me and of my Laws;</l>
               <l>By ſuffering thoſe little Foes to live.</l>
               <l>Whom I had doom'd to death without reprieve.</l>
               <l>Call them I ſay—They trembling do appear,</l>
               <l>His Viſage changed oft, as they drew near,</l>
               <l>Sure ſigns the women had juſt cauſe to fear.</l>
               <l>Then ſaid, Unhappy and ungrateful fools,</l>
               <l>Yet more blame-worthy they, who us'd ſuch tools,</l>
               <l>In things of ſo great weight and ſecrecy,</l>
               <l>You are made up of lies and flattery.</l>
               <l>Had you been wiſe and juſt in that affair</l>
               <l>That was intruſted to your (only) care,</l>
               <l>My woes had ended, and that curſed race</l>
               <l>Been raz'd or bury'd in the fertile place</l>
               <l>They now enjoy,—Speak.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great, Sir, if Oaths be ſacred, we are true,</l>
               <l>Who ne're meant good to them, nor ill to you.</l>
               <l>In this affair we not blame-worthy are,</l>
               <l>To drown their Infants was our greateſt care.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Hebrew</hi> Women, ſtronger much than ours,</l>
               <l>Have painleſs labour, they ſay higher pow'rs</l>
               <l>Aſſiſt them; and if ſo, their God is kind,</l>
               <l>'Twas both againſt our intereſt and mind.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48379:9"/>Our ſearch of late can find no birth of
theirs,</l>
               <l>Nor nothing like it, only them at pray'rs.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſwore by Sacred Moon and Sun,</l>
               <l>That he would finiſh what he had begun;</l>
               <l>In ſpite of all (ſaid he) their Blood I'll have,</l>
               <l>Although in Blood I wallow to my Grave.</l>
               <l>He frown'd, Heav'n ſmil'd, and ſaid, I'll interpoſe,</l>
               <l>I'll ſhow my pow'r, love, will, in ſaving thoſe</l>
               <l>Whom I long ſince for my own Servants choſe.</l>
               <l>I am reſolv'd out of that hated race</l>
               <l>To raiſe up one ſhall dare him to his face;</l>
               <l>And this he knows, tho I have made him blind</l>
               <l>To all the Scourges are for him deſign'd;</l>
               <l>His cloſe Cabals my Wiſdom ſhall defeat,</l>
               <l>Whom I deſtroy I firſt infatuate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſpoke, 'twas done, for <hi>Amram</hi> did eſpouſe</l>
               <l>A Wife of his own Tribe, of his own Houſe,</l>
               <l>Who had by him before this Edict came</l>
               <l>A hopeful pair, <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her third Conception which ſhe did bring forth</l>
               <l>A Son of Beauty was, who promis'd worth,</l>
               <l>Whom ſhe (afraid) hid in a ſecret place,</l>
               <l>And there him ſuckled for full three months ſpace</l>
               <l>At laſt, true Faith and Fear in her did ſtrive,</l>
               <l>This bid her drown, and that keep him alive.</l>
               <l>Faith urg'd, that ſhe a <hi>Levite</hi>'s Daughter holy,</l>
               <l>Should not be guilty of ſo great a folly,</l>
               <l>So great a crime as to deſtroy her Son,</l>
               <l>But chooſe to dye, ſay'ng Heav'ns will be done.</l>
               <l>To which her tim'rous Tongue made this reply,</l>
               <l>The King's command is urgent, then if I</l>
               <l>Be apprehended in this Fact, all, all</l>
               <l>The <hi>Hebrew</hi> Nation for my fault will fall.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48379:9"/>No, I will truſt the Babe with
providence,</l>
               <l>When I have uſed means for his defence,</l>
               <l>Such are the care ev'n of omnipotence.</l>
               <l>She ſaid, and reach'd her hand unto the Flags,</l>
               <l>Of which a Boat-like Cradle lin'd with Rags</l>
               <l>She made, and cork'd with ſlimy Pitch all o're,</l>
               <l>Leſt it ſhould ſink, if driven from the ſhore,</l>
               <l>And plac'd him there as if he went to ſleep,</l>
               <l>Committing both to Heav'n and to the deep.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Hid Rocks, roughs Seas, fierce Pyrates, Shelves and Sand,</l>
               <l>'The Merchants fear, and yet come ſafe to Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now Horrour-ſtruck, in haſte ſhe <hi>Miriam</hi>
calls,</l>
               <l>Come, come my dear, ſee'ſt thou not yonder walls.</l>
               <l>Haſte, haſte thee thither, if thou lov'ſt thy Mother,</l>
               <l>And ſee the laſt of my dear Boy, thy Brother.</l>
               <l>Stand at a diſtance, grieve not, ſhed no tear,</l>
               <l>Look pleaſantly on all, then nothing fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis eaſier to give Counſel than to take,</l>
               <l>'The burthen's light that's on another's back.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She had not long been a Spectator there,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter, thro the Almighty's care,</l>
               <l>Was brought 'bout Sun-ſet to the calmed Creek,</l>
               <l>Where th' Infant lay, his life or death to ſeek,</l>
               <l>Who ſaw the Ark, and to her Ladies ſaid,</l>
               <l>Draw up this toy, if any thing be laid</l>
               <l>In it I'll ſee; when opend, ſhe eſpy'd</l>
               <l>A lovely Child, who hung the Lip and cry'd.</l>
               <l>O Girl! ſaid ſhe, this is a glor'ous thing,</l>
               <l>I read in's face the Fortunes of a King.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48379:10"/>Come, come, my dear, I'm raviſh'd with thy
charms,</l>
               <l>Come, come and graſp a Princeſs in thy arms!</l>
               <l>I have no Heir, Dear, thou ſhalt be my Son,</l>
               <l>Dear unto me, as if my Fleſh and Bone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Siſter buoy'd with this Spring-Tyde of joy,</l>
               <l>This unexpected reſcue of the Boy,</l>
               <l>With much aſſurance to the Princeſs bows,</l>
               <l>Say'ng, Great Madam, in that Neighbouring houſe</l>
               <l>There is a Woman who is neat and tall,</l>
               <l>Of fair complexion, the Graces all:</l>
               <l>Sit on her brow in pureſt red and white,</l>
               <l>Perhaps her beauty may the Prince delight,</l>
               <l>She loves your Grace, altho an <hi>Iſraelite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egyptian</hi> or <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſaid the Queen,</l>
               <l>I like the character, when I have ſeen.</l>
               <l>The perſon, her I for his Nurſe will
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake,</l>
               <l>And ſhew her kindneſs for my Darlings ſake.</l>
               <l>Call her. She came in haſte; the Queen of Love</l>
               <l>Sent her half dreſt and left the reſt to <hi>J'ove:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who plac'd ſuch Graces on her humble heart,</l>
               <l>As made her much more beautiful than Art</l>
               <l>Could ever boaſt; her mein, his words, her gate,</l>
               <l>Beſpoke her Miſtreſs of a better ſtate,</l>
               <l>And now it's come, proſperity ne're comes late.</l>
               <l>Whom when the Princeſs ſaw, ſhe lift her eyes</l>
               <l>And hands aloft, bleſſing her Deities</l>
               <l>For this unlook'd for kindneſs, then her hand</l>
               <l>She grip'd, and ſaid, I thought that
<hi>Goſhen</hi>-Land,</l>
               <l>Had not been bleſt with Beauties ſuch as you.</l>
               <l>To which ſhe (bluſhing) anſwer'd, my brow,</l>
               <l>Great Madam, once was fair, alas! but now,</l>
               <l>It's tann'd with grief—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48379:10"/>
               <l>Such Sun-burn'd faces I am pleas'd to ſee,</l>
               <l>Reply'd the Princeſs, take this Boy from me;</l>
               <l>I did a Nurſe for him intend before,</l>
               <l>Whom he deſpis'd, try you my Knave once more.</l>
               <l>Her Snow-like Breaſts expos'd, their veins diſplay,</l>
               <l>By which, tho young, he knows the milky way,</l>
               <l>Then ſmiling, capers, ſnatches, ſighs and draws</l>
               <l>The Pipes that drain the Nectar from thoſe <hi>Spaws:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Infant toil the Queen beholds with joy,</l>
               <l>And ſmiling ſaid, your face hath caught the Boy;</l>
               <l>Keep him, fair Nurſe, he's yours and mine, I'll pay.</l>
               <l>This heard to Heav'n, ſhe ſilently did ſay,</l>
               <l>Thou great Protector of th' <hi>Iſtiades,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For this high favour I will ever bleſs</l>
               <l>Thy Sacred name, and daily pay the vow</l>
               <l>I made to thee, when my Eſtate was low.</l>
               <l>Then to the Princeſs ſhe made this reply,</l>
               <l>Your Goddeſs-like Commands I will obey,</l>
               <l>My life, and all that's dear I'll ſacrifice</l>
               <l>For you and yours, and for this Heav'n giv'n prize.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'If Providence and beauty do unite,</l>
               <l>'They make th' <hi>Egyptian</hi> love the
<hi>Iſra'lite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'When winged Chymiſts made, and gave the charm</l>
               <l>'Nor <hi>Nile,</hi> nor <hi>Egypt</hi> could the Infant
harm.</l>
               <l>'The Mothers fear by Heav'n was made the key,</l>
               <l>'T' unlock the Providential myſtery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Raptures of joy, tho violent and ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Admit allays, when mixed with the throng</l>
               <l>Of future events, and as quickly gone</l>
               <l>As was her bliſs, when ſhe receiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Son;</l>
               <l>Not from a Fiſhes womb, dead, and decay'd,</l>
               <l>But from the hand half <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Scepter ſway'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48379:11"/>To whom he muſt return when he is
wean'd,</l>
               <l>(Such Princely Nurs'ries cannot be detain'd)</l>
               <l>Not to make Bricks, but for a Diadem,</l>
               <l>'Twas to that end the Princeſs gave the name,</l>
               <l>By Heav'ns appointment, <hi>Moſes,</hi> as if ſhe</l>
               <l>From <hi>Abraham</hi> had drawn her Pedigree:</l>
               <l>A fatal blow to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Tyranny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wean'd, and return'd, his lively looks and ſport</l>
               <l>Are now the common ſubject of the Court:</l>
               <l>None like young <hi>Moſes,</hi> none hath equal ſhare</l>
               <l>With him in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s love, in's Daughters care.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> his chief Tutors are,</l>
               <l>To teach him Wiſdom, and the art of War;</l>
               <l>Wiſdom to rule, and Conduct to defend</l>
               <l>His Subjects well, from ill his helpleſs friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now he's thought fit to ſit above the beſt</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Peers, and yet is not at reſt.</l>
               <l>The reaſon of his name when call'd to mind,</l>
               <l>He knew it <hi>Hebrew,</hi> this his Soul inclin'd</l>
               <l>To do ſome great thing for his Country's eaſe,</l>
               <l>Yet loth his 'doptive Mother to diſpleaſe:</l>
               <l>He ſees, and hears their Miſeries and cries,</l>
               <l>Without concern, Court Gaudy Butterflies</l>
               <l>Dazled his youthful Eyes, the ſilken Nets</l>
               <l>Of honour wreath him ſo, that he forgets</l>
               <l>Himſelf, his name, and for ſome time confin'd</l>
               <l>His heart and hands from that he had deſign'd;</l>
               <l>But all thoſe charms were loathſome when he ſpy'd</l>
               <l>A wounded <hi>Hebrew,</hi> (of which wound he dy'd)</l>
               <l>Bathed in Blood. What? Slave, ſaid he, (none by)</l>
               <l>Muſt theſe men work, and yet your Victims lye:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48379:11"/>Thy life ſhall pay for his; this fatal
Dart</l>
               <l>Thrown by my hand, ſhall pierce thy env'ous heart,</l>
               <l>And ſhall expel thy Soul, that all may ſee</l>
               <l>The juſt reward of this thy cruelty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Return'd to Court, his grief next night did break</l>
               <l>His wonted reſt, he muſt riſe and go back</l>
               <l>To ſee his friends, and to ſuppreſs their foes.</l>
               <l>Thus did commence his hardſhips and his woes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Night-Tapers were not yet extinguiſhed,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Titan</hi> ſtarted from his watry bed,</l>
               <l>When he in haſte unto the Kilns repairs,</l>
               <l>With penſive mind, and head perplext with cares,</l>
               <l>About his Brethrens uſage, Bondage ſnares.</l>
               <l>He comes and ſees, a ſad amazing ſight,</l>
               <l>Two <hi>Jews</hi> in hot diſpute and fiercer fight,</l>
               <l>With whom he mildly did expoſtulate</l>
               <l>About the riſe of their unkind debate.</l>
               <l>Say'ng, is it not enough that en'mies beat,</l>
               <l>Kill, and abuſe you? this unnat'ral heat</l>
               <l>Will work your ruin. He that gave the cauſe</l>
               <l>Said, you begin too ſoon to frame new Laws.</l>
               <l>What? muſt a beardleſs ſtripling be our Judge,</l>
               <l>Who is more fit with us to be a drudge,</l>
               <l>If that ſuffice to expiate his crime,</l>
               <l>Committed yeſterday about this time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'When Heav'n deſigns for men, things great and good,</l>
               <l>'They are deſpis'd, becauſe not underſtood.</l>
               <l>'<hi>Moſes</hi> is ſent to free them from their woes,</l>
               <l>'Yet they're the firſt proclaim themſelves his foes;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48379:12"/>'That ſcorn his Counſel: threat'ning to
declare</l>
               <l>'How <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Servants by him treated are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This like a rapid Cataract o'reflow'd</l>
               <l>His Soul with fear: which his ſad count'nance ſhow'd</l>
               <l>Who ſighing (from a bleeding heart) thus ſaid,</l>
               <l>The thing is known, alas! I am betray'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharoah</hi> will hear't: who me already hates</l>
               <l>I will not fall into his hands, the fates</l>
               <l>Shall guide my wandring ſteps; none knows what he</l>
               <l>(Who only knows events will do with me.</l>
               <l>His Providence may find a ſafer place</l>
               <l>VVith Foreigners (perhaps) of milder Race:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe pity will preſerve me from diſgrace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> Farewel—He is no ſooner gone</l>
               <l>But his eſcape unto the King is flown,</l>
               <l>And cauſe aſſign'd: which they thus aggravate,</l>
               <l>This is the fruit of pity; our poor State</l>
               <l>VVill quickly dwindle to an empty name,</l>
               <l>Unleſs you find out means to quench this flame,</l>
               <l>It is unſufferable! Our great Monarch's blood</l>
               <l>VVill be as cheap if they be not withſtood,</l>
               <l>And we their ſlaves. The King enraged ſaid,</l>
               <l>Hark! fooliſh Girl, your Son ſo magnify'd,</l>
               <l>Is turn'd already Traytor to my Crown,</l>
               <l>Slights your Relation, Favours doth diſown,</l>
               <l>My Subjects he hath killed for their care</l>
               <l>No man can tell what his pretenſions are,</l>
               <l>But I'll prevent him, leſt he go too far.</l>
               <l>His death (when found) ſhall let the <hi>Hebrews</hi>
ſee</l>
               <l>That dreams are vain, their viſions fallacy,</l>
               <l>And that their famed God may ſometimes lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48379:12"/>
               <l>Strict ſearch is made for him about the Court,</l>
               <l>City and Suburbs where he did reſort,</l>
               <l>But all in vain; his Angel-Providence</l>
               <l>Before next light, convey'd him far from thence,</l>
               <l>And made him ſtrange, inviſible to all</l>
               <l>VVho ſought his blood, who ſought his Nations fall.</l>
               <l>The Deſart now's his Inn, the Rocks his Bed,</l>
               <l>He muſt no more with delicates be fed;</l>
               <l>But travel hard, and eat ſuch nat'ral fare,</l>
               <l>As by kind <hi>Sol</hi> and Earth produced are:</l>
               <l>Lemmons and Chaſe-nuts, Mellons, Mangoes, Rice,</l>
               <l>Oranges, Almonds, Nutmegs and their Spice.</l>
               <l>His Drink the Milk of Coco's mixt with Wine,</l>
               <l>That thro Earth's boſom ſecretly doth twine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'A gen'rous Breaſt is equally content</l>
               <l>'With Plenty, Poverty or Baniſhment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſings of his adventures by the Well,</l>
               <l>Near unto which the <hi>Midian</hi> Prieſt did dwell.</l>
               <l>He ſings his Birth, his Cradle, Rapid <hi>Nile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He ſings his reſcue with a pleaſant ſmile,</l>
               <l>The Princeſs fondneſs, and her Father's care,</l>
               <l>He ſings the cauſe why all theſe blaſted were;</l>
               <l>And then the quiet of a Hermit-life</l>
               <l>Free from the cares at Court, and Country ſtrife,</l>
               <l>The joys accruing by a virtuous wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Daughter heard, whoſe daily care</l>
               <l>Was that their Herds and Flocks well water'd were.</l>
               <l>Tho to their grief, they often were conſtrain'd</l>
               <l>To wait the riſing of the VVell, when drain'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48379:13"/>By ſurly Swains, who with their Cattle
came,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that water had the praiſe of fame.</l>
               <l>'Twixt frown and ſmile (this noble Soul diſdain'd</l>
               <l>To ſee the daily wrongs the Maids ſuſtain'd)</l>
               <l>He ſaid, dull Souls, is this your carriage</l>
               <l>To theſe fair Nymphs? Doth neither Sex nor Age,</l>
               <l>Nor beauty charm you? Will you ne'er be brave,</l>
               <l>And ſhew that Shepherds ſcorn both Clown and Knave?</l>
               <l>Cold Miſts and Dews their florid beauties break,</l>
               <l>When Froſt and Hail your Faces fairer make;</l>
               <l>For ſhame forbear, if you be Great <hi>Pan</hi>'s race,</l>
               <l>Fill up the Troughs, and give theſe Maidens place.</l>
               <l>Sir we are yours: ſince they with you find grace,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Shepherdeſſes ſoon diſpatched are,</l>
               <l>Who haſtening home, the firſt that did appear</l>
               <l>Was the old Prieſt, whoſe fears diſperſed were.</l>
               <l>What! come ſo early? are the Flocks all well?</l>
               <l>You look as if you hadſome News to tell.</l>
               <l>Yes Reverend Sir, a noble Perſonage,</l>
               <l>Of aſpect fair, courteous above his Age,</l>
               <l>By's Habit (nothing elſe) <hi>Egyptian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Drew all our water after we began,</l>
               <l>And curb'd our Rivals for their inſolence.</l>
               <l>VVhere is the Hero ſtood in your defence?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'He's great and good, the Gods themſelves you know,</l>
               <l>'Have Human Shapes and Actions when below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haſte to the Well, he may
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>em thence remove,</l>
               <l>And ſay, our Parents muſt requite his love.</l>
               <l>Arm'd with Command, they ran in winged haſte</l>
               <l>To their deliverer, and him thus addreſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48379:13"/>Fair ſtranger, we ſuch favours thought
was due</l>
               <l>From every Swain, much more from ſuch as you:</l>
               <l>VVho for the matchleſs Glories of your face,</l>
               <l>Your ſprightly looks, your grave and graceful pace,</l>
               <l>My juſtly claim precedence of your race.</l>
               <l>VVe home-bred, baſhful wenches went away,</l>
               <l>VVithout thanks giv'n, not knowing what to ſay.</l>
               <l>But coming timely home, we did relate</l>
               <l>To our old Father <hi>Raguel,</hi> our fate,</l>
               <l>How you our quarrel boldly did debate;</l>
               <l>Water'd our Flocks, and bid us all adieu.</l>
               <l>Who ſaid, I bluſh to hear ſuch things from you,</l>
               <l>Ingratitude makes all things black you know.</l>
               <l>Go, ſay I'm reſtleſs till I ſee his face,</l>
               <l>T' excuſe your rudeneſs, know his name and race.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'The Roſie morn ſuch Beauties ne're diſplay'd,</l>
               <l>'Such bluſhes and ſuch ſmiles, as did the Maid</l>
               <l>'And Stranger, who reciprocally dart</l>
               <l>'Equal deſires, as if they'd had on heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bold with the charm, he took and kiſt her hand,</l>
               <l>Say'ng Fair Nymph ſince you've received command</l>
               <l>To offer me this honour, I will go,</l>
               <l>As they deſire, my name and race I'll ſhew,</l>
               <l>That, and much more I to you beauty owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'The ſighs, the ſmiles, and the endearing ſtrains,</l>
               <l>'Paſt 'twixt our Lovers, as they croſt the plains,</l>
               <l>'Are thoughts too high for any but ſuch Souls,</l>
               <l>'As <hi>Venus</hi> ſoftens with <hi>Circean</hi> Bowls.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He comes, ſalutes, and ſoon acquaintance had</l>
               <l>With <hi>Raguel, Jethro</hi> and <hi>Zipporah,</hi> who
ſaid</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48379:14"/>Bluſhing, Dear Sir, I love this ſtranger
well,</l>
               <l>Perſwade him (if you can) with us to dwell.</l>
               <l>Heav'n rules the Stars, the Stars our Actions guide,</l>
               <l>All which portend that I ſhall be his Bride;</l>
               <l>And if my judgment fail not, you will ſee</l>
               <l>Him prop and glory of our Family,</l>
               <l>He hath in's Face ſuch Beams of Majeſty.</l>
               <l>Your pardon, Sir, with your conſent I crave</l>
               <l>To be his wife, for he a wife will have.</l>
               <l>How know'ſt thou that, fond Girl? Sir, at the Well</l>
               <l>I heard him ſing (unſeen) and he ſung well.</l>
               <l>Moſt of the Subject myſtical but this,</l>
               <l>He ended with the praiſe of Marriage bliſs.</l>
               <l>Be not too forward, he may change his mind,</l>
               <l>And after all, prove peeviſh or unkind;</l>
               <l>'Tis rare a conſtant Courtier to find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some time is ſpent in viewing of the place,</l>
               <l>The Herds, the Flocks, the Buildings and the Graſs;</l>
               <l>The manner of their Living, and their Laws,</l>
               <l>Sacred and Civil, their ſweet Springs and <hi>Spaws.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The ſtranger ſhew'd his great content in all,</l>
               <l>And wiſh'd himſelf the woolly General</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Jethro</hi>'s bleating arms, and that he</l>
               <l>Might be a Servant in that Family.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Had you ſeen <hi>Venus</hi> in her Robes Divine,</l>
               <l>'Or <hi>Helen</hi> in <hi>Corinthian</hi> bravery ſhine;</l>
               <l>'Young <hi>Paris</hi>'s love, but now the ſport of fame,</l>
               <l>'The <hi>Greeks</hi> diſturber, and the <hi>Trojans</hi>
ſhame:</l>
               <l>'Or <hi>Rachel</hi> fair, when in her nat'ral dreſs,</l>
               <l>'Whom at the Well the Patriarch did careſs,</l>
               <l>'Then at our <hi>Zipporah</hi>'s Beauty you might gueſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48379:14"/>
               <l>When ſhe appear'd in ſplendour like love's Queen,</l>
               <l>All on a flame, and yet would not be ſeen</l>
               <l>To be her Martyr. <hi>Jethro</hi> muſt make way,</l>
               <l>Who to our Gallant (ſmiling) thus did ſay.</l>
               <l>Sir, doth our Country pleaſe? Can any thing</l>
               <l>Within my reach to you contentment bring?</l>
               <l>Speak freely, all is yours, my joy, my life,</l>
               <l>My eldeſt Daughter you may have to wife.</l>
               <l>Dear <hi>Zipp.</hi> what ſay'ſt thou to this choice of
mine.</l>
               <l>My deareſt, Sir, ſaid ſhe, this great deſign</l>
               <l>May be above my Merits; yet ſince yours,</l>
               <l>I do ſubmit. O! may the higher Pow'rs</l>
               <l>Direct us all.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'When brave <hi>Leander</hi> boldly ventured,</l>
               <l>'O're <hi>Hell eſpont</hi> by fatal Torches led;</l>
               <l>'When mighty <hi>Jove</hi> came down in Golden Show'rs,</l>
               <l>'Nor <hi>Hero</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
charms, nor <hi>Danae</hi>'s, had more Pow'rs</l>
               <l>'Than <hi>Zipp'ra</hi>'s eyes, and <hi>Jethro</hi>'s well-tun'd
breath.</l>
               <l>'The ſtranger (bluſhing) ſaid, I'm yours to death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Joynt promiſe giv'n, and rites all conſummate,</l>
               <l>Our Lovers, now, are in a fearleſs ſtate,</l>
               <l>Baſhful and coy no more, their Bed is one,</l>
               <l>Till pregnant <hi>Zipporah</hi> had a hopeful Son.</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Moſes Gerſhom</hi> nam'd, himſelf to mind</l>
               <l>Of th' entertainment he on earth ſhould find.</l>
               <l>A ſtranger there, he was; tho lov'd and known,</l>
               <l>Tho <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Houſe and Flocks were as his own.</l>
               <l>Where he abode until the time was come</l>
               <l>That <hi>Pharaoh</hi> from the fates muſt have his doom.</l>
               <l>Tho Kings be Gods, they cannot ſcape the Tomb.</l>
               <l>Whoſe unlamented fall the <hi>Hebrews</hi> cheer'd,</l>
               <l>Who ſaid, by our new King we may be heard;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48379:15"/>But all their hopes and wiſhes proved
vain,</l>
               <l>Their Tasks are doubled, and the Lab'rers ſlain.</l>
               <l>This made them ſigh, this made them pray and cry</l>
               <l>To Heav'n, that he no longer would deny</l>
               <l>His promis'd aid, who call'd his word to mind,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, I muſt to <hi>Iſrael</hi> be kind;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Abra'm, Iſaac,</hi> and for <hi>Jacob</hi>'s
ſake,</l>
               <l>Their Fetters I'll knock off, their Chains I'll break.</l>
               <l>Now, I think fit to eaſe, and ſet them free</l>
               <l>From their heart-breaking ſorrows, ſlavery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>''Twas I that ſuffer'd <hi>Joſeph</hi> to be ſold,</l>
               <l>'Impriſon'd and releas'd; 'twas I enroll'd</l>
               <l>'His name with <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Worthies, it was I</l>
               <l>'That gave the wiſdom, him did dignify;</l>
               <l>'I moved <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to ſend for the Father,</l>
               <l>'I taught the Son all <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Corn to gather</l>
               <l>'Before the Famine; I gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> grace</l>
               <l>'With <hi>Egyt</hi>'s King, and choſe for him a place:</l>
               <l>'<hi>Goſhen</hi> (the fair) where he in wealth did
flouriſh,</l>
               <l>''Twas I his num'rous Family did nouriſh</l>
               <l>'(When dead); 'twas I his Bones to <hi>Canaan</hi> ſent,</l>
               <l>'A pledge of's Children's future ſettlement.</l>
               <l>'It is for reaſons to me only known,</l>
               <l>'They have not yet enjoy'd it, tho their own.</l>
               <l>'But now they ſhall the beſt of Lands inherit,</l>
               <l>'Becauſe I love them, not becauſe they Merit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fodder ſpent, and <hi>Midian</hi> Paſtures bare,</l>
               <l>Religious <hi>Moſes</hi> doubleth his care</l>
               <l>To find out Graſs; at laſt his Flocks he brings</l>
               <l>Unto the back of <hi>Horeb,</hi> where the Springs</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48379:15"/>Are limpid, ſalutiferous, and where</l>
               <l>The Paſtures good, and Sky is always clear,</l>
               <l>And gladſome Spirits have fam'd dwellings there.</l>
               <l>Here, he with patience waits th' accompliſhment</l>
               <l>Of Heav'ns promiſe, and what elſe Heav'n meant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Angel-God, to haſten his deſign</l>
               <l>Appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d as man, but
cloath'd with Light Divine:</l>
               <l>A buſh ſurrounding with Celeſt'al fire,</l>
               <l>This ſight mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> diſcompos'd, retire.</l>
               <l>The flame was hot and fierce, yet frighted more,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the Shrubs ſtood verdant as before.</l>
               <l>With penſive thoughts mov'd, he lookt backt to ſee</l>
               <l>The end of this (yet unknown) myſtery,</l>
               <l>Taking it for a ſign of victory</l>
               <l>O're ſome Great Prince—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heaven ſees, and calls him twice,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes, Moſes</hi> be curious, take advice;</l>
               <l>Look to thy Feet, and make no raſh advance,</l>
               <l>This place is holy, ſign of importance.</l>
               <l>I'm no deceitful, nor fictitious <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho in this buſh, I am the God of Love.</l>
               <l>He in whom <hi>Abra'm</hi> truſted, <hi>Iſaac</hi>
fear'd,</l>
               <l>And for whoſe honour <hi>Jacob</hi> Altars rear'd.</l>
               <l>That ſeen, this heard, the trembling Shepherd bows,</l>
               <l>Juſt ſentiments of both in's face he ſhews,</l>
               <l>With vailed Eyes, not daring more to ſee,</l>
               <l>Suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ful beams of ſplendid majeſty</l>
               <l>As had the Author of this prodigy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whilſt he in this dejected poſture lay,</l>
               <l>(His ſences lockt) not knowing what to ſay,</l>
               <l>A ſweet, refreſhing, ſoft, melodious voice,</l>
               <l>Revives his Spirits, and bids him rejoyce,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48379:16"/>Say'ng, the promis'd time is fully come</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s freedom, and th' <hi>Egyptian</hi>'s
doom.</l>
               <l>It was not my forgetfulneſs that did</l>
               <l>Protract their Bondage, my eyes were not hid,</l>
               <l>Nor bowels hard, my Providence requir'd</l>
               <l>That they ſhould firſt with <hi>Egypt</hi>'s fare be
tir'd,</l>
               <l>And worſhip too—</l>
               <l>I muſt now for my ancient promiſe ſake,</l>
               <l>For which Truth, Juſtice, Goodneſs, are at ſtake,</l>
               <l>Uſe ſuch ſure methods as ſhall bring them back.</l>
               <l>All their oppoſers ſhall before them fall,</l>
               <l>That brutiſh Nation ſhall no more enthral</l>
               <l>The Off-ſpring of my Friends, I've heard their cry,</l>
               <l>And am come down their wrongs to rectify;</l>
               <l>Their Sorrows to remove, their State to change,</l>
               <l>From making Bricks, to cultivate a Grange</l>
               <l>That's large and fruitful, whoſe Inhabitants</l>
               <l>(Their cup now full) ſhall be expos'd to wants.</l>
               <l>My Peoples plaints I cannot longer bear,</l>
               <l>Without redreſs, revenge on them that tear</l>
               <l>Their Hearts with Tongues and Hands, it is my will,</l>
               <l>Go thou to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and bid him fulfil,</l>
               <l>The Lords commands and ſend his Friends away,</l>
               <l>Doubt not th' event, I <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Sceptre ſway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To this the baſhful Shepherd anſwer made,</l>
               <l>Great God, thou know'ſt the meanneſs of my Trade,</l>
               <l>And rural dreſs, make me unfit to ſpeak</l>
               <l>With <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of a buſineſs ſo great,</l>
               <l>For 'tis to ſpoil a Tyrant of his prey,</l>
               <l>Who threat'neth death to all that diſobey</l>
               <l>His abſolute commands, I know long ſince</l>
               <l>No good can be expected from that Prince.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48379:16"/>
               <l>Courage my Friend, look great, the work is mine,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Pharoah</hi> frown, and Hell with him combine;</l>
               <l>Thou by my pow'r, ſhall finiſh this deſign,</l>
               <l>And when my people thou doſt from him take,</l>
               <l>See, on this Mountain thou an Altar make,</l>
               <l>For their deliv'rance, and mine honours ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lord, ſaid the Shepherd, this great prodigie</l>
               <l>Confirms my feeble faith, which yields to thee;</l>
               <l>Yet when I unto them this Meſſage carry,</l>
               <l>They'll ſcoff and ſay, this mad man makes us merry,</l>
               <l>Who ſent thee hither? tell us what's his name?</l>
               <l>Or own thy ſelf a Fool, and bluſh for ſhame.</l>
               <l>What anſwer muſt I give to this demand,</l>
               <l>Let me obtain this favour at thy hand,</l>
               <l>If I muſt go?—My being is immence,</l>
               <l>I am, I was, I will be, get thee hence;</l>
               <l>By this I to their Fathers was well known,</l>
               <l>And they the ſame (if theirs) will likewiſe own,</l>
               <l>But if they ſcruple at this Myſtic name,</l>
               <l>Say, you from me, the God of <hi>Abra'm</hi> came,</l>
               <l>Who long ſince, unto him a promiſe gave,</l>
               <l>(His prov'dence ſerv'd by <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s being
ſlave</l>
               <l>In <hi>Egypt</hi>) he would them in <hi>Canaan</hi> place,</l>
               <l>This is my name to all the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> race.</l>
               <l>Thou muſt be chief in this great enterprize,</l>
               <l>Haſte unto <hi>Egypt,</hi> call the grave and wiſe</l>
               <l>Amongſt the Tribes, and thy commiſſion ſhow,</l>
               <l>By its contents the author they will know;</l>
               <l>No circumſtance of that thou muſt with-hold</l>
               <l>Hath been tranſacted here by me, be bold;</l>
               <l>Relate the place, the Perſon, words and ſign,</l>
               <l>By which they'll know it is no mock deſign,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48379:17"/>Tell them, that now I with a melting
eye,</l>
               <l>Behold their ſorrows, burthens, miſery,</l>
               <l>And by a powerful hand will bring them forth</l>
               <l>From <hi>Egypt</hi>'s bondage, publiſhing their worth</l>
               <l>To <hi>Canaanites</hi> and <hi>Hittites,</hi> who ſhall
give</l>
               <l>The Houſes unto them in which they live.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Amorites</hi> and <hi>Perizites</hi> ſhall ſay,</l>
               <l>The Land's not ours, ariſe, we muſt away;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Hivites</hi> and the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> ſhall
haſte</l>
               <l>Out of their place; ſaying, 'tis th' Almighti's waſte,</l>
               <l>Which he on his own Friends will now beſtow,</l>
               <l>Where moſt, and beſt, of Fruits ſhall ever grow,</l>
               <l>And Milk and Honey like the Waters flow.</l>
               <l>When they hear this all quickly will agree</l>
               <l>To act as they directed are by thee,</l>
               <l>Then loſe no time, but haſte unto that King,</l>
               <l>And ſay, you tydings from <hi>Jehovah</hi> bring:</l>
               <l>Who charges all the Tribes on pain of Death,</l>
               <l>By Sacrifices, to appeaſe his wrath;</l>
               <l>Entreat that he may grant a grant a gracious ear</l>
               <l>Unto his Servants, who their God do fear:</l>
               <l>Three days no more, you beg for this affair,</l>
               <l>Which ended, they ſhall back to him repair.</l>
               <l>The Wilderneſs is near, the fitteſt place</l>
               <l>To ſue for Pardon, Pity, and for Grace,</l>
               <l>Renew their vows, and ſee his bleſſed Face.</l>
               <l>Tho I am ſure the refractory King</l>
               <l>Will give no leave, nor credit to the thing.</l>
               <l>He will not let them go, your prayers their tears,</l>
               <l>Will have repulſe from his vindictive ears,</l>
               <l>Yet be not daunted, his vain boaſts ſhall tend</l>
               <l>To <hi>Egypt</hi>'s utter ruin in the end,</l>
               <l>The wonders I will work ſhall ſoon incline</l>
               <l>His tow'ring Sp'rit to favour my deſign,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48379:17"/>And make his Subjects give their helping
hand,</l>
               <l>(With all they have) to ſend you from the Land.</l>
               <l>With all their Gold, and Jewels they will part,</l>
               <l>Silver and Cloaths, all which with willing heart</l>
               <l>They'll give your Children, that they may depart:</l>
               <l>So you ſhall be requited for your toyl,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Egypts</hi>'s furnace, with <hi>Egyptian</hi>
ſpoil.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Heav'n ſits at Helm in weather foul and fair,</l>
               <l>'The Living Cargo's his peculiar care,</l>
               <l>'The Sails may ſplit, and Maſts come by the board,</l>
               <l>'The Ship may leak, and Pumps no help afford,</l>
               <l>'The Maſter, Mates, and Saylors may complain,</l>
               <l>'Of Ship and lofty Winds; but all in vain;</l>
               <l>'The Waves muſt ſwell and bulge the Ship, or ſtave</l>
               <l>'The cutting keel, if Mighty <hi>Jove</hi> give leave.</l>
               <l>'But Pray'rs and Tears that Heav'n do always pleaſe,</l>
               <l>'Make the Storm ceaſe, and ſmooth the foaming Seas,</l>
               <l>'Bringing all ſafe to Land, with joy and eaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Lord, ſaid <hi>Moſes,</hi> I well knew the men,</l>
               <l>To my great grief, forty years ſince, for then</l>
               <l>By ſecret inſtinct (ſure it was from thee)</l>
               <l>I made a ſtep to their delivery,</l>
               <l>Which early act they for injuſtice took,</l>
               <l>And make me leave a Sceptre for this hook,</l>
               <l>This ancient odium ſtill alive, I fear</l>
               <l>Will harden their proud hearts, and ſtop their ear,</l>
               <l>Their Unbelief that's heightned by their grief,</l>
               <l>Hath from them baniſhed all thoughts of relief,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48379:18"/>So that my words (I'm ſure) they'll not
believe,</l>
               <l>Unleſs ſome ſign from thee I to them give,</l>
               <l>Their Souls are dead, 'tis thou muſt make them live.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If I give ſigns, think'ſt thou that ſigns will do?</l>
               <l>Go, ſhow them ſigns from me, and wonders too,</l>
               <l>What's in thine hand? My Lord a Shepherds Crook,</l>
               <l>Throw't on the Ground, and on it ſharply look,</l>
               <l>What is it now? A Dragon, horrid, great,</l>
               <l>All men ſuch creatures mortally do hate.</l>
               <l>Fear not, lay hold upon its twiſting tail,</l>
               <l>Tho it look fierce its ſting ſhall not prevail,</l>
               <l>But to the former form it ſhall return.</l>
               <l>The Buſh of late which flamed did not burn.</l>
               <l>Now put thy hand into thy boſom, where</l>
               <l>It may be free from hurt, infectious air,</l>
               <l>Haſte take it out. Ah! Lord I am undone,</l>
               <l>This Leproſie will cleave unto the bone.</l>
               <l>What! Faithleſs ſtill? put in thy hand again,</l>
               <l>Behold, it's well and free from ſcurf or ſtain,</l>
               <l>Diſtruſt no more.—If they'll not credit give</l>
               <l>To the firſt ſign, the ſecond they'll believe,</l>
               <l>If neither doth their faithleſs hearts affect,</l>
               <l>So as to hear thee, I will then direct</l>
               <l>Another way, by which thou may'ſt perſwade</l>
               <l>That you from me this grand commiſſion had,</l>
               <l>Out of fam'd <hi>Nile</hi> fair water thou ſhalt take,</l>
               <l>Which pour'd upon the ground, my pow'r ſhall make,</l>
               <l>Great cakes of clotted blood, ſhall terrifie</l>
               <l>The King and them, then all ſhall yield to thee,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Let Earth with Earth, Mortal with Mortal ſtrive,</l>
               <l>'Like Waſps and Bees, when fighting for the Hive,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48379:18"/>'Let men contend with men, and let them
dare</l>
               <l>'Each other as they liſt, yet take great care,</l>
               <l>'They fight not him, whoſe creatures they are;</l>
               <l>'His powerful Juſtice can ſoon animate</l>
               <l>'A Rod that's dry into a Serpent great,</l>
               <l>'Make Water Blood, and what elſe he thinks fit,</l>
               <l>'To overthrow their policies and wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is not all, Dear God, my ſtamm'ring tongue</l>
               <l>(For want of Elquence may do much wrong,</l>
               <l>Unto this cauſe thou orderſt me to plead,</l>
               <l>(Not with with the Vulgar, but) with thoſe that lead</l>
               <l>The reſt, with whom nothing will reliſh well,</l>
               <l>But what with art, and florid words doth ſwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A weak excuſe, ſince thou well know'ſt that I</l>
               <l>Have made mans mouth, his heart, his ear, his eye,</l>
               <l>If dumb men ſpeak, deaf hear, or blind men ſee,</l>
               <l>No cauſe for theſe can be aſſign'd but me:</l>
               <l>Up then, and with undaunted courage go,</l>
               <l>I will be always with thy mouth; if ſo,</l>
               <l>Thy Tongue ſhall like a ready Writers Pen,</l>
               <l>Such reaſons give all ſhall convince all men.</l>
               <l>This burden, Lord's to heavy for my back,</l>
               <l>And thou haſt many ſtronger, ſome one take</l>
               <l>This ſervice to perform; let me ſtill keep,</l>
               <l>The tender Flocks of <hi>Jethro,</hi> Kids and Sheep,</l>
               <l>As heretofore.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Look on this buſh, ungrateful, fearful man,</l>
               <l>Leproſie, Serpent, Blood, then (if you can)</l>
               <l>Deny obedience to his juſt commands,</l>
               <l>Who promiſeth to guide thy mouth and hands.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48379:19"/>It is thy Wiſdom, not thy Liſping
Tongue,</l>
               <l>I chooſe for this tranſaction; one is ſprung</l>
               <l>From the ſame ſtock with thee, who ſhall declare,</l>
               <l>With art Divine, what my intentions are,</l>
               <l>And how I think to order this affair.</l>
               <l>He's on the road, and big with expectation,</l>
               <l>Since I inform'd him, how the <hi>Hebrew</hi> nation</l>
               <l>Should by my pow'r, his word, thy hand, be freed,</l>
               <l>And bloody meaſures broke, that were decreed,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Egypt</hi> for their ruin.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Give this in charge, when he doth firſt appear,</l>
               <l>That when to <hi>Goſhen</hi> he doth back repair,</l>
               <l>He may, nor art, nor words, nor labour ſpare,</l>
               <l>Both of you ſhall be ſtrengthned from above,</l>
               <l>To ſhow that I afflicted <hi>Iſrael</hi> Love,</l>
               <l>And ſhall have joynt commiſſion, he thy mouth</l>
               <l>Shall be, and thou to him as God of truth:</l>
               <l>This Rod's the inſtrument that you muſt uſe</l>
               <l>This Vengeance working Rod, on thoſe refuſe</l>
               <l>T' 'bey my will, that mighty Monarch ſhall</l>
               <l>By this dry Wand deſpiſed be, and fall,</l>
               <l>I ſay be gone—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Heav'n could not be, nor in that Heav'n a <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'If Earth could ſcan the ſecrets of his Love;</l>
               <l>'How he contrives, deliberates, decrees,</l>
               <l>'The fates of private Men and Monarchies;</l>
               <l>'His wiſdom is a Sea, that hath no bottom,</l>
               <l>'His providence a depth that none can fathom;</l>
               <l>'His Wills a Law none ought to diſobey,</l>
               <l>'In Heav'n and Earth, he doth the Sceptre ſway;</l>
               <l>'To Friends he is kind, to enemies auſtere,</l>
               <l>'Yet Juſtice holds the ballance here and there.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48379:19"/>'He wants not agents to effect his will,</l>
               <l>'That Fiſhermen or Shepherds can fulfil;</l>
               <l>'If men were wanting, Water, Earth, dry Rods,</l>
               <l>'Can force the ſtubborn to obey the Gods.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This new poſt doth not <hi>Moſes</hi> elevate</l>
               <l>Above the thoughts of his (late) low eſtate,</l>
               <l>Tho he be choſe Heav'ns Envoy, he doth go</l>
               <l>Firſt unto <hi>Midian</hi> that his friends may know,</l>
               <l>Their Shepherd muſt on Embaſſy be ſent</l>
               <l>To <hi>Eyypt,</hi> whence he came in Baniſhment,</l>
               <l>His Kindreds burthen to condole and try,</l>
               <l>(Once more) his Fate for their delivery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The news when <hi>Jethro</hi> heard, he ſighing ſaid,</l>
               <l>My deareſt Son I wiſh my feeble aid</l>
               <l>Could any way aſſiſt you in this task,</l>
               <l>It ſhould be giv'n before you could it ask,</l>
               <l>My Prayers and Tears ſhall be that God direct</l>
               <l>And grant the ſucceſs you from him expect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'The enemies of God and of his Laws,</l>
               <l>'Submit for ſecret, not for open cauſe;</l>
               <l>'<hi>Jethro</hi> is willing with his Son to part,</l>
               <l>'The ſtaff of's Life, the joy of's Daughters heart,</l>
               <l>'Tho for that loſs he afterward may ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Night had no ſooner ſhut the Shepherds eye,</l>
               <l>Than he a ſplendid Viſion did eſpy,</l>
               <l>Of form divine; who thus itſelf expreſt,</l>
               <l>Sleep on, my Friend, ſleep on, and take thy reſt;</l>
               <l>Then up, and haſte to <hi>Egypt,</hi> for its ſtrife</l>
               <l>'Gainſt thee is ended with that Monarch's life.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:48379:20"/>'When Angels guard, and give the opiate,</l>
               <l>'Men reſt ſecure, nothing can hurt or hate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before next light gilded that Hemiſphere</l>
               <l>The Shepherd wak'd, ſaid <hi>Zipporah,</hi> my Dear,</l>
               <l>I've for thy love, and for our livelihoods</l>
               <l>In Deſarts liv'd, in Mountains, and in Woods</l>
               <l>Theſe forty years, where my integrity</l>
               <l>Was known to all, my greateſt love to thee:</l>
               <l>Now, Heav'n reſolv'd to alter my condition,</l>
               <l>Sends me to <hi>Egypt:</hi> Dear, let no ſuſpicion</l>
               <l>Of fraud or hatred harbour in thy breaſt,</l>
               <l>My God commands, and his commands are beſt.</l>
               <l>I'm wholly yours, ſaid ſhe, Heav'ns will be done,</l>
               <l>Tho Nature bids me grieve when left alone;</l>
               <l>You know that Man and Wife are fleſh and bone.</l>
               <l>Life of my Soul, nothing can us two part,</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt I ever had a tender heart</l>
               <l>Since firſt I ſaw, and helpt thee at the Well.</l>
               <l>True, true, my Dear, I am content to dwell</l>
               <l>Where you think fit. What muſt we take from hence?</l>
               <l>Only the Boys, the reſt to Providence</l>
               <l>I will commit, except this holy Wand,</l>
               <l>Which I muſt always carry in my hand,</l>
               <l>And wonders work with it in that curſt land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'None but the Lover knows the grief to part</l>
               <l>'With that is lov'd, ſince both have but one heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heav'n calls again, and bids him when he ſees</l>
               <l>The faithleſs King, make fair diſcoveries</l>
               <l>Of his Intentions, and the fearful end</l>
               <l>He for his ſtubbornneſs will on him ſend.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48379:20"/>I know he'll raging ſay, think'ſt that I
will</l>
               <l>Diſmiſs my Slaves, thy humour to fulfill?</l>
               <l>No, they have ſworn to be mine for ever,</l>
               <l>In this opinion I will perſevere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To this reply, when they came firſt, 'tis true,</l>
               <l>They ſaid their Lives and Fortunes were your due,</l>
               <l>Ingratitude they ſcorn'd whilſt you was kind,</l>
               <l>Freſh obligations them anew did bind,</l>
               <l>And they're the ſame, tho you have chang'd your mind,</l>
               <l>But now their God commands, who hath a right</l>
               <l>O'er them, and you, whoſe wiſdom, valour, might,</l>
               <l>None can oppoſe, when he's reſolv'd to fight.</l>
               <l>He ſaith, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was his firſt-born Son,</l>
               <l>And muſt (tho now your Slave) in haſte be gone,</l>
               <l>If thou perſiſt in diſobedience,</l>
               <l>Thy firſt born kill'd, he'll force his people hence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Good Kings are Heav'ns beloved, mankinds joy,</l>
               <l>'Whilſt they their time and counſels do employ</l>
               <l>'To rule with juſtice, clemency and love,</l>
               <l>'In imitation of their King above,</l>
               <l>'Whilſt they reſolve their conduct to confine</l>
               <l>'Within the limits of the Law Divine,</l>
               <l>'Which give them eaſe, and firmly fix their Crown,</l>
               <l>'Procure mens favour, bring new bleſſings down</l>
               <l>'Upon their heads and hearts, but when their will</l>
               <l>'Is reſtleſs as the Sea, that ne'er lyes ſtill,</l>
               <l>'But beats th' adjacent Rocks, and plows the Sands,</l>
               <l>'Threat'ning a Deluge o're the fertile Lands,</l>
               <l>'Smiting the great, and blaſting thoſe below,</l>
               <l>'With ſubtle Lightning ſlighting friend and foe,</l>
               <l>'Such <hi>Jehu</hi>'s, curſt, are their own overthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48379:21"/>
               <l>Away he goes, not fearing ill ſucceſs,</l>
               <l>Since potent Heav'n eſpous'd his buſineſs,</l>
               <l>And travels hard till mid-day's ſcorching Sun</l>
               <l>Be at on his head, which forc'd him to ſit down</l>
               <l>Under a ſhady Beech, where angry <hi>J'ove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Appear'd again, not as before in love,</l>
               <l>His aſpect threat'ned death, which had enſu'd,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Zipp'rah</hi> had not ſoftned the cloud,</l>
               <l>Who run in haſte unto her younger Son,</l>
               <l>And cut his fore-skin with a flinty Stone,</l>
               <l>Then took the ſame, and threw't at <hi>Moſes</hi> feet,</l>
               <l>With unbecoming words ſhe did him greet.</l>
               <l>Is your juſt God with human blood aton'd,</l>
               <l>Muſt Kings for his diſpleaſure be dethron'd?</l>
               <l>Muſt Women to their darlings Tygers prove,</l>
               <l>T' oblige a cruel God? Is this his Love?</l>
               <l>Hard hearted man, hard hearted as thy God,</l>
               <l>I cannot, will not longer bear this load,</l>
               <l>That you call Superſtition pleaſeth me,</l>
               <l>I will return, yet let me hear from thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Mixt matches often prove unfortunate</l>
               <l>'To private men, and always to the State.</l>
               <l>'Love, multitudes of Nuptial faults can cover,</l>
               <l>'But when Religion's one, all are paſt over,</l>
               <l>'One God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s enough;
more make all diſagree,</l>
               <l>'Religious Brawls put out Religions eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aaron,</hi> who many years had griev'd to ſee</l>
               <l>His brethrens bondage, burthens, miſery,</l>
               <l>Receiv'd command from Heaven to walk abroad,</l>
               <l>To meet his Brother <hi>Moſes</hi> on the road,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48379:21"/>Returning home, and bids him liſten
well</l>
               <l>To all ſuch matters as he ſhould reveal.</l>
               <l>This news like Balſome, his chill'd heart did warm,</l>
               <l>His Sp'rits revive, and all his Senſes charm,</l>
               <l>He car'd not what, or whom he left behind,</l>
               <l>O'rejoy'd, he ſhould his exil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Brother find</l>
               <l>Alive. He haſtes unto the Mount of God</l>
               <l>To meet him (for he there ſome time abode.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Salutations paſt, and tears diſtill'd,</l>
               <l>Expreſſions of the joy, their hearts that fill'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> to his, gives vent by this diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>Is <hi>Jochebed</hi> alive, my Mother, Nurſe?</l>
               <l>Are <hi>Amram, Mirian,</hi> and the reſt all well?</l>
               <l>Yes, deareſt Brother; as when you did dwell</l>
               <l>In <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court, this one exception made,</l>
               <l>Our burdens are encreas'd, tho <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s dead.</l>
               <l>This I well know, the reſt I'm joy'd to hear,</l>
               <l>Said <hi>Moſes,</hi> but I've wonders to declare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſr'el</hi> muſt be releas'd from <hi>Egypt</hi>'s
woe,</l>
               <l>I have command from Heav'n to tell you ſo.</l>
               <l>See! here's my ſeal'd Commiſſion in my hand</l>
               <l>And Weapon too, that <hi>Memphis</hi> muſt command,</l>
               <l>With thy aſſiſtance, I will work ſuch ſigns,</l>
               <l>As ſhall that King deſtroy and his deſigns.</l>
               <l>This is the bus'neſs, thou art eloquent,</l>
               <l>Show thine the cauſe why I am hither ſent.</l>
               <l>Up, let us go, we muſt the Elders call,</l>
               <l>Publiſh our freedom and our en'mies fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'To <hi>Caleb</hi> once God gave another Spirit,</l>
               <l>'<hi>Eliſha</hi> did <hi>Elijah</hi>'s gift inherit.</l>
               <l>'<hi>David</hi> did wiſely play, <hi>Saul</hi>
propheſie,</l>
               <l>'When they command receiv'd from God on high.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48379:22"/>'So baniſht <hi>Moſes</hi> after forty
years,</l>
               <l>'Returns with power to eaſe his brethrens fears,</l>
               <l>'Their groans, their ſighs, and their heart-breaking
tears,</l>
               <l>'And <hi>Aaron</hi> who did work or overſee,</l>
               <l>'Is Trumpet made for their delivery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who thus began—My deareſt brethren here,</l>
               <l>(If Liberty you love, or your God fear)</l>
               <l>What Heav'n by <hi>Moſes</hi> hath bid me reveal</l>
               <l>The wonders muſt be done, that he may heal</l>
               <l>All your diſeaſes. If you ſigns muſt have,</l>
               <l>Time ſhall bring forth as many as you crave.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, the Tribes rejoycing, anſwer'd all,</l>
               <l>We do believe our riſe, and <hi>Egypt</hi>'s fall,</l>
               <l>And ſince our ſad affliction Heav'n hath 'ſpy'd,</l>
               <l>Our Song ſhall be, let Heav'n be magnify'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'When Tempeſts riſe, and Clouds pour down their Rain,</l>
               <l>'The faint and feebled Footmen cry amain,</l>
               <l>'Help kindeſt Heav'n, and ſend us Halcyon days,</l>
               <l>'There is no walking in ſuch dirty ways.</l>
               <l>'He hears, the ſtorm's allay'd, and clouds appear</l>
               <l>'Serene, a bleſſing to the traveller,</l>
               <l>'Such were theſe tydings to each Jewiſh ear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Council up, and all the Elders gone,</l>
               <l>They leave the Brothers to conſult alone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe next concluſion's to inform the King</l>
               <l>Of what for him, they from <hi>Jehovah</hi> bring,</l>
               <l>Great Sir, ſaid they, the King of Kings commands</l>
               <l>You his Viceroy to ſlacken <hi>Iſraels</hi> bands,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:48379:22"/>That they a juſt, a pious people, may</l>
               <l>Reſt from their tasks, to ſacrifice and pray:</l>
               <l>We will no tumult make, when we remove</l>
               <l>Into the Deſart, let us beg your love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'The ſacrifices of a broken heart,</l>
               <l>'The pray'rs and vows men unto Heav'n impart,</l>
               <l>'Need neither pompous ſhows, nor glozing art,</l>
               <l>'He hears in ſecret in the Wilderneſs,</l>
               <l>'In Mountains Chriſt himſelf made his addreſs,</l>
               <l>'Who never pray'd without his wiſh'd ſucceſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Impudence! Treaſon! cry'd the Heathen King,</l>
               <l>Fairies, not Men, from their black <hi>Pluto</hi> bring</l>
               <l>Such freakiſh fancies. Who's your Lord, that I</l>
               <l>At ſuch a diſadvantage ſhould obey,</l>
               <l>To ſet my Slaves, my drudging Vaſſals free;</l>
               <l>I know him not, and there's no ſuch decree</l>
               <l>In my Archieves; Vile vagabonds be gone,</l>
               <l>You ſpeak as if you would attempt my Throne,</l>
               <l>I will not let them go—</l>
               <l>They add, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> God us hither ſent,</l>
               <l>The God of Order and of Government,</l>
               <l>By whom Kings Reign, 'tis his prerogative</l>
               <l>At pleaſure to recall what he doth give,</l>
               <l>Who now requires, that you forthwith releaſe</l>
               <l>His friends from ſlav'ry to their wonted eaſe,</l>
               <l>With leave to go unto the Wilderneſs.</l>
               <l>Diſmiſs the men we pray, for three days ſpace,</l>
               <l>We are deſtroy'd if you deny this grace.</l>
               <l>To which th' incenſed King made this reply,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> why do ye defie</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Edicts, you are more than mad,</l>
               <l>To cheat theſe people, and deſtroy my trade,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48379:23"/>Give o'er, and let them work, it is my
will,</l>
               <l>They muſt and ſhall their former tasks fulfil.</l>
               <l>Think you that I ſuch numbers can maintain</l>
               <l>In idleneſs and ſloath, you muſt abſtain,</l>
               <l>Elſe your grave plot will quickly prove a ſham,</l>
               <l>And they repent that you unto them came:</l>
               <l>Call the Task maſters of theſe Slaves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I'll know</l>
               <l>The reaſon why my work goes on ſo ſlow.</l>
               <l>Unnatural Rogues, did I not ſtrictly charge</l>
               <l>That you their wonted burthens ſhould enlarge,</l>
               <l>It's your connivance, that is worthy blame,</l>
               <l>It makes them think the Embaſſy that came</l>
               <l>Was by divine appointment, but I'll ſee</l>
               <l>What God they ſhall adore, if't be not me.</l>
               <l>Double their Tasks, ye Dogs, let no ſupply</l>
               <l>Be giv'n for their aſſiſtance, Straw nor Hay,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill demand full tale as heretofore,</l>
               <l>When they had their materials from my ſtore.</l>
               <l>Go, tell the Zealots that (of late) they're Idle.</l>
               <l>Go, laſh their backs, I'll make them bite the Bridle,</l>
               <l>Muſt I be rival'd by I know not who?</l>
               <l>Or by two Knaves cajol'd to let them go.</l>
               <l>No, they ſhall know I rule—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Court Paraſites as ſoon as they receive</l>
               <l>'A royal Nod, they'll ſwear that <hi>Caeſar</hi> gave</l>
               <l>'Them pow'r by Inuendo to confound</l>
               <l>'<hi>Babel</hi> with <hi>Bethel,</hi> vile with holy ground,</l>
               <l>'Their Will's their Law, prerogative pretence,</l>
               <l>'To act a gainſt Religion, Reaſon, Senſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus arm'd, theſe Officers away do fly,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s preſence, piercing the wide Sky,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iſra'ls</hi> Hearts with their blood-thirſting
cry.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:48379:23"/>Religious Fops, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will give
no Straw,</l>
               <l>Since you deny obedience to his Law,</l>
               <l>And ye from you full tasks of Bricks will draw,</l>
               <l>Or we muſt beat you dead, there's no reprieve,</l>
               <l>Unleſs your nameleſs God doth you relieve.</l>
               <l>It's Harveſt now, haſte you unto the Fields,</l>
               <l>The new reapt grounds this year much ſtubble yields,</l>
               <l>That gather, and fulfil your work as when</l>
               <l>The Straw was giv'n. Expect it not agen.</l>
               <l>They try'd, but all in vain, to do the thing,</l>
               <l>Which on their heads another ſtorm did bring</l>
               <l>From th' enraged Task-maſters who ſay,</l>
               <l>Why have you not made up your tale this day,</l>
               <l>Nor yeſterday, as you have done before,</l>
               <l>Think on your Bricks, and play the fool no more.</l>
               <l>If you are moved with our harſh diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Pharaoh</hi> you may have your next recourſe,</l>
               <l>Perhaps your treatment may be worſe than ours.</l>
               <l>Like drowning men who graſp at every reed,</l>
               <l>This feign'd affection their faint hopes doth feed.</l>
               <l>They ran and ſaid, Dread Soveraign we know</l>
               <l>That we our ſelves are yours, and labours owe</l>
               <l>Unto this State. We truſt therefore that ye</l>
               <l>For pities ſake will alter the decree,</l>
               <l>Publiſh'd againſt us by your royal will,</l>
               <l>That without Straw, our tasks we ſhould fulfil.</l>
               <l>If this be in our pow'r, Great Sir, be judge,</l>
               <l>(Tho uſe and hardſhip have taught us to drudge)</l>
               <l>We're beaten without fault, they are the cauſe</l>
               <l>Who counſel firſt, and then deſire that Laws</l>
               <l>May be enacted, on pretence of good</l>
               <l>To <hi>Egypt,</hi> but we know it's for our blood,</l>
               <l>For which they long have thirſted, and expect</l>
               <l>By your command that murder to effect,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:48379:24"/>Prevent them Sir. No, no, you idle be</l>
               <l>I cannot, will not alter my Decree,</l>
               <l>Your new devotion made you over-quick,</l>
               <l>Go hence and work, I'll ſhow you trick for trick,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'As long beſieged Caſtles when they ſee</l>
               <l>'A bloody Flag hung out, when Soldiers be</l>
               <l>'Decoy'd to Ambuſcade, when Seamen fling</l>
               <l>'Their Maſts o'er board, Bale, Goods and ev'ry thing:</l>
               <l>'Or when the nighted Trav'ller falls in pit,</l>
               <l>'And men condemn'd in darkeſt Dungeons ſit,</l>
               <l>O'erwhelm'd with endleſs grief, ſuch was the ſtate</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s bondmen, when the knew their fate,</l>
               <l>'One ſwounds, one cryes, one tears his hairs and breaſt,</l>
               <l>'Another rageth, deſperate the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſhall we do, ſaid they? See! <hi>Moſes</hi>
comes,</l>
               <l>Let's meet him, and relate our fearful dooms</l>
               <l>Now paſt on us, upbraid him, he's the cauſe</l>
               <l>Of our deſtruction, by theſe bloody Laws.</l>
               <l>Ah! cruel man, ran thy Commiſſion thus,</l>
               <l>Thou ſaid'ſt Heaven bid thee publiſh unto us?</l>
               <l>We'd better much never have ſeen thy face,</l>
               <l>Than ſuffer thus, by work, ſtripes and diſgrace.</l>
               <l>If juſt ſuch methods are, let Heav'n be judge,</l>
               <l>Before thou cam'ſt we wrought, we did not drudge;</l>
               <l>But thy ungrateful meſſage to the King</l>
               <l>Hath made us loathſome unto every thing</l>
               <l>That is in <hi>Egypt;</hi> thy bold, bitter words</l>
               <l>Sharpen their hearts againſt us, as their Swords,</l>
               <l>This they, with fury in their looks expreſs,</l>
               <l>Would thou had'ſt ſtay'd yet in the Wilderneſs,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48379:24"/>We at our burthens then, we might have
had</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Egyptian</hi>'s love; with Straw for our Brick
trade,</l>
               <l>Both now are loſt, and we our ſelves in danger</l>
               <l>To be deſtroyed in our Monarch's anger.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> diſtruſting what might be th' event</l>
               <l>Of this harſh menace, highly diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Look'd pale and trembled, grief ſo ſeiz'd his heart,</l>
               <l>That neither <hi>Aaron</hi>'s love nor <hi>Aaron</hi>'s art,</l>
               <l>Could cure thoſe wounds (tho green) they did ſo ſmart,</l>
               <l>This made him have recourſe unto the Lord,</l>
               <l>And peremptor'ly ſay, who can thy word</l>
               <l>Believe hereafter; ſince our firſt attempt</l>
               <l>Is ſhamefully repuls'd with ſcorn, contempt,</l>
               <l>This was my fear, when thou to me didſt ſay,</l>
               <l>Go unto <hi>Egypt,</hi> bring my Sons away,</l>
               <l>Thy promiſes to us increaſe our pain,</l>
               <l>Why didſt thou ſend me? I'll return again</l>
               <l>To <hi>Midian;</hi> ſince I ſee thy providence</l>
               <l>Promotes our ſorrows, not deliverance,</l>
               <l>The Tribes deſpair of (ever) going hence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tho Providence be beautiful and bright,</l>
               <l>'And brings things that moſt hidden are to light.</l>
               <l>'It often works by means that contrary are</l>
               <l>'To Human Reaſon (for it Reaſon far</l>
               <l>'Exceedeth) yet it hath the wiſhed end,</l>
               <l>'Good to the good man, and the good mans friend.</l>
               <l>''Twas providence that made young <hi>Joſeph</hi> dream,</l>
               <l>'His Parents and his brethren were the theme,</l>
               <l>'By which his future fortunes were diſplay'd,</l>
               <l>'Tho he knew neither what he dreamt or ſaid,</l>
               <l>'Yet for that dream was envy'd, ſold, betray'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:48379:25"/>Falſely accus'd, condemn'd to priſon
faſt;</l>
               <l>Strange ſteps! to make him <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Lord at
laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What! Faithleſs <hi>Moſes?</hi> fearful, doſt thou
fret?</l>
               <l>Why ſtumbleſt in the Porch? the time's not yet</l>
               <l>Fulfilled for the work, wait, thou ſhalt ſee</l>
               <l>What I will do 'gainſt <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> what, for thee.</l>
               <l>I'll call my thund'ring Legions from above,</l>
               <l>To force your paſſage, that you may remove,</l>
               <l>In ſpite of your oppoſers, <hi>Egypt</hi>'s King</l>
               <l>Shall willingly to you aſſiſtance bring.</l>
               <l>It is to me a wonder that you ſhould</l>
               <l>Diſpute my promiſes ſince <hi>Abra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> could</l>
               <l>Without ſuch, firmly reſt upon my pow'r,</l>
               <l>For all he had from's his birth to's his dying hour</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>El-ſhaddaj</hi> to him was ſufficient,</l>
               <l>And to his children whitherſo'er they went;</l>
               <l>They ſcarce the name <hi>Jehovah</hi> e'er did ſpell,</l>
               <l>But of <hi>Adonia</hi> talkt, and lik'd that well.</l>
               <l>When I to them of <hi>Canaan</hi> promiſe made,</l>
               <l>They truſted in my pow'r and always ſaid,</l>
               <l>What! tho we ſtrangers be? Our God can give</l>
               <l>This and much more: altho we may not live</l>
               <l>To ſee it done, it is enough that ours</l>
               <l>Shall of that Land be the inheritors.</l>
               <l>The time is come, my patience is abus'd,</l>
               <l>My Servants by proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſo ill us'd,</l>
               <l>That their ſad groans, which I ſeem'd to deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Have mov'd my juſtice, now I muſt ariſe</l>
               <l>To vindicate my truth, revenge the ſpite</l>
               <l>Acted on every ſuffering <hi>Iſraelite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hope ſtill in me, my promiſe I'll not break,</l>
               <l>I will redeem you for my promiſe's ſake.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:48379:25"/>Go to the Tribes, and ſay, I am the
Lord,</l>
               <l>I cannot falſify, recal my word.</l>
               <l>I'll bring them forth from under <hi>Egypt</hi>'s yoke,</l>
               <l>And gently lead them; they're my tender flock,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> paſtures where they may</l>
               <l>In ſafety ſleep, wake, ſacrifice and pray,</l>
               <l>Without diſturbance, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> nor his land,</l>
               <l>Shall take them out of the Almighty's hand,</l>
               <l>My formidable actions when they ſee</l>
               <l>Their might and rage ſhall truckle under me.</l>
               <l>Then I with mine my Cov'nant will renew,</l>
               <l>My Love is great although they be but few.</l>
               <l>I will go with them to the wilderneſs,</l>
               <l>Where with my preſence I'll begin their bliſs,</l>
               <l>If they obſtruct not their own happineſs.</l>
               <l>They <hi>Canaan</hi> ſhall poſſeſs, it ſhall be
theirs,</l>
               <l>By firm entail for them and for their Heirs.</l>
               <l>I will make good whatever I have ſaid,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that God, who the firſt promiſe made,</l>
               <l>Which you will own, when I th' <hi>Egyptian</hi> King,</l>
               <l>With all his Subjects to deſtruction bring.</l>
               <l>Then be no more ſhame-fac'd, of fearful heart,</l>
               <l>Go, all theſe tydings to the <hi>Jews</hi> impart</l>
               <l>I know they're vexed, and will not believe</l>
               <l>That I th' Almighty can give a Reprieve</l>
               <l>From their hard bondage. Go unto the King,</l>
               <l>Who (peeviſhly) will ask what news ye bring?</l>
               <l>To which, with boldneſs you ſhall anſwer make,</l>
               <l>Thy Slaves are Freemen now, they muſt go back</l>
               <l>From whence they came—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Who would not be Religious, and fears</l>
               <l>'The wonder-worker; whoſe great mercies are</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48379:26"/>'Fixt as the Winters Moon, and Summer
Son</l>
               <l>'(Laſting when both are ſcorched up and done)</l>
               <l>'His promiſes, his favour, and his grace,</l>
               <l>'Were ever ſuch to the <hi>Iſacides.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> revolving his late reprimand</l>
               <l>Receiv'd from <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> (with a palſied hand</l>
               <l>And trembling tongue) ſaid, Lord, it is in vain</l>
               <l>To offer this unto the Tribes again:</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Aaron</hi>'s words, nor my great ſigns they have</l>
               <l>Regarded hitherto, why ſhould I crave</l>
               <l>That of a wrathful King which they'll deny?</l>
               <l>Since I can neither of them gratify.</l>
               <l>—Are theſe your thoughts? you better things might
know,</l>
               <l>—Your fear makes you thus ſcrupulouſly ſlow,</l>
               <l>—How dares man ſtay, when Heavens bids him go.</l>
               <l>Diſtruſt no more, your God doth undertake</l>
               <l>This wondrous task, and for that end will make</l>
               <l>Thy pow'rful ſigns bring down great <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s heart,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Aaron,</hi> as thy mouth, ſhall act his part.</l>
               <l>Exceed not thy commiſſion, ſay no more</l>
               <l>To him, than I to thee have ſaid before.</l>
               <l>This bid him freely unto <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſay,</l>
               <l>Heav'ns choſen Servants muſt not longer ſtay</l>
               <l>In his Dominions; their increaſed woe</l>
               <l>Is at an end, they muſt to <hi>Canaan</hi> go.</l>
               <l>I know his rage, his fury he'll deny</l>
               <l>Thy God, or thee in this to gratify,</l>
               <l>From's hard'ned heart my ſpirit I'll remove,</l>
               <l>His Conſcience him ſhall no more warnings give</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:48379:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Of my diſpleaſure, nor his future
ſtate;</l>
               <l>The Devil ſhall him deceive till it's too late,</l>
               <l>I'll blind his judgment ſo, that he ſhall be</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt actor in's own tragedy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Like Fiſh unwary plung'd into the Net,</l>
               <l>'The more they ſtrike, the faſter in they get,</l>
               <l>'So he (while all my wonders I have ſpent.</l>
               <l>'Not dreaming that his own deſtruction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s meant)</l>
               <l>Shall boldly with enchanting Witch-crafts dare,</l>
               <l>'The ſigns by thee and <hi>Aaron</hi> acted are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know he'll ſtrive my Outguards to defeat,</l>
               <l>Not knowing that I have more wonders yet</l>
               <l>At my command; whole Armies that can dye</l>
               <l>His waters Crimſon; darken his bright Sky.</l>
               <l>My word ſhall bring poor vermin from their Cells</l>
               <l>Will him deſpiſe, and all his Magi's ſpells.</l>
               <l>The winged. Troops I've ready at my beck,</l>
               <l>His ruin, <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s reſcue to effect.</l>
               <l>That tawny King and all his ſwarthy crew,</l>
               <l>Shall that with vengeance learn, they never knew.</l>
               <l>I will the Winds let looſe, and Seas adjure</l>
               <l>With him to make the fatal overture,</l>
               <l>For bringing <hi>Iſrael</hi> out by my great pow'r.</l>
               <l>I know when you before him (next) appear</l>
               <l>Your perſons he will ſcorn, yet ſay draw near,</l>
               <l>You, who pretend a meſſage from above,</l>
               <l>Muſt it confirm by Miracles; or prove</l>
               <l>Your ſelves Impoſtors, Rebels to my Crown.</l>
               <l>Moſt willingly, ſay you, and then throw down</l>
               <l>This pregnant Rod; which turning to a Snake,</l>
               <l>Shall twiſt, unfold and crawl, and ſtrive to take</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:48379:27"/>The Royal Scepter out of <hi>Pharaoh's</hi>
hand,</l>
               <l>At which he (much affrighted) mute will ſtand,</l>
               <l>Nodding and ſighing, for his Sophi-band.</l>
               <l>They come. He ſaid, what think my Prieſts of this?</l>
               <l>Can you ſuch Serpents turn, and make them hiſs;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas! great Sir, ſaid they, this fellow's art</l>
               <l>Was learn'd from us, before he did depart</l>
               <l>Thy Predeceſſors Court, and now he brings</l>
               <l>Owls into <hi>Athens,</hi> we know better things.</l>
               <l>Look on our Rods, Great Sir, which we command</l>
               <l>By all our Deities, to turn from our hand</l>
               <l>(As that of his) to many Serpents great</l>
               <l>And when all's done, both his and ours are cheat.</l>
               <l>Legerdemain can make falſe things appear</l>
               <l>To th' ignorant, as if they real were.</l>
               <l>But here is more, ſaid he, his ſwalloweth yours,</l>
               <l>This) if a trick) I'm ſure's beyond your pow'rs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well, <hi>Moſes</hi> this is fine, but yet I muſt</l>
               <l>See more and greater things, before I truſt</l>
               <l>That you commiſſion have from any God</l>
               <l>To rob me of my Subjects; <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod</l>
               <l>And all your charms for this will prove in vain,</l>
               <l>Once more be gone, and from theſe ſlights abſtain,</l>
               <l>This will not eaſe, but more increaſe your pain.</l>
               <l>Then turn'd and frown'd, and ſaid diſdainfully,</l>
               <l>I'm King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> I your God defie!</l>
               <l>I ſcorn to think of a ſuperiour,</l>
               <l>Who can make Gods. I'll hear of him no more</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'This heard, in haſte the flaming Seraphs came</l>
               <l>'To pay their homage, Cherubs did the ſame,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:48379:27"/>'Say'ng Holy, Holy, Holy Lord and true!</l>
               <l>'How long have we bleſt Spirits honour'd you,</l>
               <l>'Both night and day, not daring once to pry</l>
               <l>'Into the ſecrets of ſuch Majeſty?</l>
               <l>'Yet in our tarvels at your beck, we hear</l>
               <l>'Proud Mortals talk as they your Rivals were.</l>
               <l>'Your patience we've experienc'd in our ſelves,</l>
               <l>'Whom you confirm'd in grace: but that ſuch elves</l>
               <l>'As they ſhould ſharers of this goodneſs be</l>
               <l>'Is unto us next to a prodigy;</l>
               <l>'Since nobler beings for one ſingle fault,</l>
               <l>'When they attempt your honour to aſſault,</l>
               <l>'Receiv'd a preſent <hi>Mittimus</hi> to go</l>
               <l>'From bliſs eternal, to eternal woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Have you ſo long domeſticks been to me</l>
               <l>'And count one ſingle Act a prodigy,</l>
               <l>'Look back on former ages, there you'll find</l>
               <l>'Greater, and more done by me of that kind,</l>
               <l>'My mercy's great, and cannot be confin'd.</l>
               <l>'When all the Sons of men like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſpoke</l>
               <l>'Reproachfully of me, and did provoke</l>
               <l>'My Juſtice, then I took a fixed time</l>
               <l>'To vindicate my ſelf, correct that crime,</l>
               <l>'And ſo I will do now.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Take ſpeedy wing</l>
               <l>To <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaying, you a meſſage bring</l>
               <l>From me. It's beſt to ſee him in the night,</l>
               <l>That he may be prepar'd when it is light,</l>
               <l>To wait on vexed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> at the River,</l>
               <l>Whoſe heart is hard and faithleſs yet as ever,</l>
               <l>And in that ſtate reſolves to perſevere.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48379:28"/>Tell him from me, that when the Monarch
views</l>
               <l>Himſelf, and <hi>Aaron,</hi> coming with freſh news,</l>
               <l>That ſight will ſo exaſperate his wrath,</l>
               <l>He'll threaten both of them with preſent death,</l>
               <l>Command him not to fear, but take his Rod,</l>
               <l>And ſay once more to him, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> God</l>
               <l>Scorns his repulſes in the buſineſs</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Iſra'l</hi>'s going to the Wilderneſs</l>
               <l>At his command.—Shall vile Earthworms deny</l>
               <l>Their maker, and refuſe to gratify</l>
               <l>His juſt demands? his pow'r will make thee know</l>
               <l>That thou allegiance unto him do'ſt owe</l>
               <l>With full obedience. Pray, Great Sir, believe</l>
               <l>For God commands that I a ſign ſhall give.</l>
               <l>Theſe limpid ſtreams that he made for thy good</l>
               <l>By this ſmall Rod ſhall turned be to blood,</l>
               <l>Blood, that to thee may fearful, loathſome be,</l>
               <l>And all its ſinn'd inhab'tants ſtupify,</l>
               <l>Thy Rivers ſhall with blood and fiſh ſo ſtink,</l>
               <l>That thine (tho fainting) may not of it drink.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, the winged Herauld took his flight,</l>
               <l>Leaving his Friend in bed curtain'd with night,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſleep was broke by th' awful Meſſenger,</l>
               <l>Who left his errand and did diſappear;</l>
               <l>The meſſage <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
bear.</l>
               <l>Confuſed ſlumbers did again invade</l>
               <l>The Prophets temples, no ſound ſleep he had,</l>
               <l>Till lofty <hi>Titan,</hi> Earth's Ethereal eye,</l>
               <l>Nights ſables tinged with a Roſie dye,</l>
               <l>Which ſhow'd him that the King was paſſed by.</l>
               <l>He dreſt and bluſht, his thoughts were on the River,</l>
               <l>Th' Almighty ſpeaks, (whoſe mercy faileth never,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:48379:28"/>Whoſe Judgments ſlumber not, when he
begins</l>
               <l>To bare his arm, and puniſh crying ſins,)</l>
               <l>Friend <hi>Moſes,</hi> do my will, it is not hid</l>
               <l>From thee, I've by my ſelf, and Angel bid</l>
               <l>That thou in this affair ſhould fearleſs be</l>
               <l>As <hi>Aaron,</hi> both direction from me</l>
               <l>From time to time ſhall have, go hand in hand,</l>
               <l>While you have brought my Sons out of the Land.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Aaron</hi> take the Rod, and ſhake it over</l>
               <l>Their Rivers and their Ponds which waters cover,</l>
               <l>And all their Veſſels, wherein they keep ſweet;</l>
               <l>That which they draw for drink, and dreſſing meat.</l>
               <l>For I will turn thoſe waters into blood,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they've hitherto my power withſtood</l>
               <l>And ſlain my ſubjects, for this cruel deed</l>
               <l>They in this puniſhment their ſin ſhall read.</l>
               <l>As blood was their delight, ſo blood ſhall be</l>
               <l>The firſt ſad ſign of their Cataſtrophe:</l>
               <l>My Infants tears I cannot longer ſmother,</l>
               <l>The griefs and groans of each diſtreſſed Mother,</l>
               <l>The Fathers loſs I do with him condole,</l>
               <l>Infanticide doth vex my very Soul,</l>
               <l>My Juſtice muſt this cruelty controul.</l>
               <l>The harmleſs waters that did ſuffocate</l>
               <l>Thoſe half-liv'd babes, ſhall ſhow my pow'r, my hate,</l>
               <l>By painted bluſhes, tho this Livery</l>
               <l>Will not yet work the wiſh'd delivery</l>
               <l>Of their ſurviving parents. Go and try,</l>
               <l>Tho he'll not me by this yet gratify.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus authoriz'd, the Brethren haſte to <hi>Nile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe early coming made the Monarch ſmile,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:48379:29"/>Stood there before: who ſaid, come
<hi>Moſes,</hi> tell</l>
               <l>Us news from Heav'n, are all things ſettled well</l>
               <l>In that <hi>Utopean</hi> Territory? ſay,</l>
               <l>Have you command to take my Slaves away?</l>
               <l>Yes Sir we have, as you're long ſhall know,</l>
               <l>None can diſtruſt thoſe good credentials ſhow.</l>
               <l>Theſe waters we will in your preſence ſmite,</l>
               <l>Waters that bring to <hi>Egypt</hi> wealth, delight,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in them you drown the <hi>Iſraelite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They ſtrike, the Flood put on a crimſon bluſh,</l>
               <l>Dy'd by the hand that ſav'd the flaming buſh:</l>
               <l>Which quickly turn'd to nauſeous putrid blood,</l>
               <l>Dazzling the Fiſhes, tho their ſight was good,</l>
               <l>They could not ſee to ſwim, nor gather food.</l>
               <l>But, wondring at the change of th' Element,</l>
               <l>Struggle for life, until their life was ſpent.</l>
               <l>The Crocodil's feign'd tears do real grow,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they could not reſt above, below,</l>
               <l>The waters running bloody, thick and ſlow.</l>
               <l>The Tortoiſes crawl from their warmer Sand,</l>
               <l>To lay and hatch their Eggs upon the Land,</l>
               <l>All ſhewing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> 'twas th' Almighty's hand.</l>
               <l>Tho he the prodigy with indignation</l>
               <l>Beholds, and calls the wiſe men of the Nation;</l>
               <l>Saying, have you this new trick never done?</l>
               <l>Are they the Wonder workers, they alone?</l>
               <l>Call up your Demons, and their aid implore,</l>
               <l>Or elſe be gone. I'll be Prieſt-rid no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt Sacred Sir, you know to us your will</l>
               <l>Is dearer than our Souls, we will fulfil</l>
               <l>All your deſires, when we clear water find,</l>
               <l>We'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l do as they have
done, and eaſe your mind,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48379:29"/>That <hi>Egypt,</hi> you, and all the world
may ſee,</l>
               <l>It is not fit ſuch Fops to gratify.</l>
               <l>Believe your Prieſts, great Sir, your doubt is o're!</l>
               <l>Well, now my heart is harden'd as before,</l>
               <l>Let us go home—My Lord what ſhall we do?</l>
               <l>Cry'd the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> (with a triple bow)</l>
               <l>Our thirſt is great, the Water none can drink,</l>
               <l>Nor eat the Fiſh (now dead) for both do ſtink,</l>
               <l>We are undone what're the wiſe men think.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Remove from <hi>Nile,</hi> deep Wells you may prepare</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor his Brother <hi>Aaron</hi> were,</l>
               <l>The ſubterraneal ſtreams, I hope, are free</l>
               <l>From Incantation, <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sorcery.</l>
               <l>Try, 'tis but ſev'n days wonder, when that's o'er,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nile</hi> will be ſweet, and clear as heretofore.</l>
               <l>When they are weary'd we ſhall have a Truce,</l>
               <l>With ſatisfaction for the loſs, abuſe,</l>
               <l>Done to our ſacred perſon, to our ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elohim</hi> frowning, crys obliterate</l>
               <l>The name of that proud Prince, his crimes require</l>
               <l>Both temp'ral Judgments, and eternal Fire.</l>
               <l>Tell him, my Juſtice (ſince he will not mend)</l>
               <l>Deſigns far greater plagues on him to ſend;</l>
               <l>His clear'd ſweet water ſhall for ſmell and taſte,</l>
               <l>Be worſe than when the blood did it infeſt;</l>
               <l>For I will call from thence a croaking hoſt,</l>
               <l>That cover ſhall the Earth with Spawn, his Coaſt</l>
               <l>Shall be diſcolour'd, no place ſhall be free,</l>
               <l>His Houſe and Bed will both infeſted be.</l>
               <l>His Servants, who have yet ſcarce trouble had,</l>
               <l>Shall eat the loathſome ſlime amongſt their bread.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:48379:30"/>Theſe Frogs, ſo faſt, ſo numerous
will come</l>
               <l>On him and his, that there ſhall be no Room</l>
               <l>Unhaunted left—I ſay go tell the King,</l>
               <l>Then with your (hallowed) Rod perform the thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Brothers go, who after honours made,</l>
               <l>Inform'd the King of what <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſaid.</l>
               <l>He ſeem'd ſecure and frown'd, they urg'd the caſe,</l>
               <l>And with a Frog-plague dar'd him to his face.</l>
               <l>Think not, ſaid they, that menaces will do,</l>
               <l>We have command to act and menace too.</l>
               <l>The Wand ſtretcht o're the ſtream, a hideous noiſe</l>
               <l>Was heard, an uncouth croak, harſh-ſounding voice</l>
               <l>Of new made Frogs, ſuch as the world's eye</l>
               <l>Ne're yet beheld—A loathſom Majeſty.</l>
               <l>Sat on their o'er grown bulks, and made them dare</l>
               <l>T' invade their Houſes, Temples, without fear,</l>
               <l>Tho newly rais'd, they train'd and valiant were.</l>
               <l>The trembling King and Country ſtrove to oppoſe</l>
               <l>The inroads of thoſe (unknown) warlike Foes;</l>
               <l>But all in vain—the more of them they kill</l>
               <l>The more they grew, the more their Houſes fill.</l>
               <l>The Palace is not free'd; the King muſt bear</l>
               <l>The greateſt burden while they quarter there.</l>
               <l>Heav'n gave the Billets, made the Court of Guard</l>
               <l>In <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Houſe; this him from ſleep
debarr'd,</l>
               <l>Who thought each Frog a dying Child, whoſe cries</l>
               <l>Pierced his heart, as theirs had pierc'd the Skies;</l>
               <l>And brought the Judgment under which he groans,</l>
               <l>Becauſe his cruel heart deſpis'd their moans.</l>
               <l>Blood-ſhed and Cruelty make empty Thrones.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:48379:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Choak'd with faint fulſome
ſmells, he left his bed,</l>
               <l>Shaking his Locks with Frogs-ſpawn overſpread,</l>
               <l>Then ſighs and ſhrieks, and weeps, and calls who's
there?</l>
               <l>To thoſe lay by; but they oppreſt with fear,</l>
               <l>Made no return. At laſt great <hi>Jambres</hi> ſpeaks.</l>
               <l>My Lord, why are you troubled at ſuch freaks?</l>
               <l>I'll make ſuch vermin, if you ſay I ſhall.</l>
               <l>No, ſuch deluſions do but haſte my fall.</l>
               <l>Call Heav'ns Envoys, <hi>Moſes</hi> and his Brother,</l>
               <l>There is a God, I cannot longer ſmother</l>
               <l>My ſentiments of this great truth, I ſee</l>
               <l>That not your art, nor love, can comfort me;</l>
               <l>You have encreas'd my Sorrows, but relief</l>
               <l>Tranſcends your pow'r. This, this augments my grief.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, ſhame, paleneſs ſeiz'd on ev'ry face,</l>
               <l>To ſee the inſolence, impet'ouſneſs</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Titan</hi>'s ſpurious brood, baſe watry race.</l>
               <l>But moſt of all o'the Wizards, who begin</l>
               <l>To ſhrivel up their Noſes, Cheeks, and Chin,</l>
               <l>Mutter and howl, becauſe they cannot awe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as formerly. He doth withdraw.</l>
               <l>They gawn and yell than <hi>Cerberus</hi> more loud,</l>
               <l>And ſo expire, Hell gaping for their blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> appears, to whom the King with tears</l>
               <l>Said, you are not inſenſible what fears,</l>
               <l>What horrors, and what miſeries attend,</l>
               <l>The man's abus'd and cheated by his friend.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:48379:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>This is my caſe, you know I have
withſtood</l>
               <l>At their deſire, that Heav'n meant for my good</l>
               <l>Peace, tho I drown'd his Servants in the flood.</l>
               <l>Now, now alas! my Land and Conſcience feel</l>
               <l>The worſt of woes, think'ſt not that Heaven may deal</l>
               <l>More mildly with me, ſince his mercy's great,</l>
               <l>Beg thou that he remove from my poor ſtate</l>
               <l>This loathſome fry—I will no more contend,</l>
               <l>But willingly his loved people ſend</l>
               <l>To offer ſacrifice. Make this thy care.</l>
               <l>I'm now convinc'd he is a God of pray'r,</l>
               <l>And thou his Servant.—This with grave accent</l>
               <l>He uttered, as tho he did repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Grand Rebels, Murtherers, and Thieves, when come</l>
               <l>'Before the Bench, expecting their laſt doom</l>
               <l>'Have mourning on, and with a pitious tone</l>
               <l>'Complain of their misfortunes, every one</l>
               <l>'Doth beg for mercy; yet if Jur' or Judge,</l>
               <l>'Or Clement King, give them from law refuge,</l>
               <l>'They grow more bold, and act as if they had</l>
               <l>'A Royal Leaſe to follow their old Trade.</l>
               <l>'Or like a Miſer, who (thro age) doth feel,</l>
               <l>'His ſeared Soul within its houſe to reel,</l>
               <l>'Cries, O this ill-got Gold! What ſhall I do?</l>
               <l>'It has deſtroy'd my Soul and Body too.</l>
               <l>'Yet for prevention I will Alms-houſe rear,</l>
               <l>'Or Chappel build, to which men may repair,</l>
               <l>'As I have ofton done, my crimes to hallow,</l>
               <l>'Straining at Gnats, that I might Camels ſwallow.</l>
               <l>'If none of theſe, I to the poor will give</l>
               <l>'A mighty ſumm, that ſo my Soul may live.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48379:31"/>'But, if of that diſeaſe he doth
recover,</l>
               <l>'O! how he frets, and acts his tricks all o'er,</l>
               <l>'With more induſtry, craft, and perjury,</l>
               <l>'Say'ng now, I am no more affraid to die.</l>
               <l>—So <hi>Pharoah</hi> griev'd with Blood, and with the
Frogs,</l>
               <l>—Calls out for <hi>Moſes,</hi> flatters, lies and
coggs,</l>
               <l>—As if he'd not been ſettled on the lees,</l>
               <l>—But rack'd and fin'd by theſe diſcoveries,</l>
               <l>—And fit with them to offer ſacrifice.</l>
               <l>—Heav'n condeſcends, and <hi>Moſes</hi> is content</l>
               <l>—With his fair words, tho the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w falſely meant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Thus <hi>Nineveh</hi>'s repentance, tho a flaſh,</l>
               <l>'Kept from its back, the Prophets threatned laſh,</l>
               <l>'And <hi>Ahab</hi>'s humbling did for <hi>Judah</hi>'s King</l>
               <l>'Obtain reprieve, tho not for his off-ſpring,</l>
               <l>'So <hi>Phaaroh</hi> for a feign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d acknowledgement,</l>
               <l>'Had half the plague remov'd, Heav'n on him ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tho thou haſt now left off ſelf-glorying,</l>
               <l>Said <hi>Moſes,</hi> thou may'ſt glory in this thing,</l>
               <l>That God in mercy will grant thy requeſt,</l>
               <l>And ſend theſe Vermin from thy land in haſte,</l>
               <l>Commanding them henceforth to make abode</l>
               <l>Within <hi>Nile</hi>'s banks.—Contend no more with
God,</l>
               <l>But pray and wait. To morrow thy ſhalt ſee,</l>
               <l>This plague remov'd, from off thy land and thee,</l>
               <l>If to thy words thou add ſincerity,</l>
               <l>Then thou ſhalt know, that none is like the Lord,</l>
               <l>Whoſe pow'r will quickly eaſe to thee afford,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:48379:32"/>We ſhall no ſooner ask than 'twill be
done.</l>
               <l>They pray, Heaven hears, the daring Frogs are gone</l>
               <l>In ſhoals to <hi>Nile,</hi> or periſht by the way,</l>
               <l>When God ſaith go, his creatures muſt not ſtay.</l>
               <l>As ſoon as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had the news receiv'd,</l>
               <l>He ſmiling ſaid, your friend may be deceiv'd.</l>
               <l>Kings can not by their promiſes be bound</l>
               <l>To <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf, their Counſellours have found</l>
               <l>Salvo's from his own word, than can oppoſe</l>
               <l>The faint aſſaults of every Monarch's foes,</l>
               <l>And I'll believe them, tho I loſe my Crown,</l>
               <l>My promiſe lately made I will not own,</l>
               <l>Nor let them go.—This the Almighty knew,</l>
               <l>Who call'd the brethren, and obedience due</l>
               <l>To his commands required, which they give,</l>
               <l>And he commands, that ſcatter'd Duſt may live,</l>
               <l>Turning to Lice, both upon man and beaſt,</l>
               <l>That might make <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſhuck, and all the
reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This done, the Itching Monarch calls aloud,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Jannes, Jambres,</hi> all the Sophi brood,</l>
               <l>Can you make Lice, ſaid he? No cry'd the Wizard,</l>
               <l>To counterfeit this thing we will not hazard,</l>
               <l>Leſt fire conſume us, or a worſer thing</l>
               <l>That after this, Heav'n may upon us bring</l>
               <l>For what's already done, for here we ſee</l>
               <l>The print of's Fingers, Pow'r and Majeſty,</l>
               <l>Which doth confound us, and our Foppery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'A fair confeſſion; but Hypocriſy</l>
               <l>'Will ſpeak the truth when't thinks the ſame a lie,</l>
               <l>'When a duluding Sp'rit infatuates</l>
               <l>'Prince, Prieſt or people to deſpiſe the fates</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:48379:32"/>'Their policy is madneſs, and their
pride</l>
               <l>'Such inſolence as God and men deride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus fared it with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> his releaſe</l>
               <l>From Blood, Frogs, Lice, preſage a fourth diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>The God of Miracles could not behold,</l>
               <l>But muſt ſubdue the proud, ſuppreſs the bold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go, <hi>Moſes,</hi> then ſaid he, by morning light,</l>
               <l>Stand before <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his peoples ſight,</l>
               <l>And let him know, it is <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s will,</l>
               <l>That he with ſpeed his juſt commands fulfil,</l>
               <l>In letting <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, that they may pay</l>
               <l>Their Homage; if he make them longer ſtay</l>
               <l>Thro his refuſal, by my next alarm</l>
               <l>A fearful Hoſt, great ſwarms of Flies ſhall arm,</l>
               <l>Which will moleſt him more than Frogs or Lice,</l>
               <l>And all his Servants bid him take advice.</l>
               <l>Say, 'tis no cheat, <hi>Goſhen</hi> ſhall make thee
know,</l>
               <l>That I my people love, and to them owe</l>
               <l>(By promiſe) freedom from the noiſome beaſt,</l>
               <l>With every thing, the greateſt and the leaſt,</l>
               <l>That may infeſt them. Tho they dwell by thee,</l>
               <l>Their Habitations ſhall no ſhelter be</l>
               <l>To thee, and thine, from ſtinging, ſtinking Flie.</l>
               <l>Obſerve this warning, ſince I ſpeak in love,</l>
               <l>Mercy, not Judgment, 'tis I moſt approve.</l>
               <l>Conſider well, the ſign will be to morrow,</l>
               <l>And will to thee beginning be of ſorrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Who can ſuch charms of love and goodneſs hear</l>
               <l>'Unleſs 't be <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and not ſhed a tear?</l>
               <l>'But ah! his Heart, his Bowels hard'ned are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:48379:33"/>
               <l>He will not let Heav'n convenanted go,</l>
               <l>But leave to ſacrifice at home, (if ſo)</l>
               <l>He gives. To which <hi>Moſes</hi> made this reply</l>
               <l>Who gives but half, he doth the whole deny,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that half is giv'n unwillingly.</l>
               <l>Our God commands us to the wilderneſs,</l>
               <l>And he beſt knows which is the fitteſt place.</l>
               <l>If among you we ſtay, then we muſt offer</l>
               <l>Such things as you, which our God will not ſuffer;</l>
               <l>If ours, it will be ſaid we innovate</l>
               <l>Your ſacred Rites and your Decrees of State;</l>
               <l>Both theſe may on us ſudden ruin being,</l>
               <l>And therefore we muſt plainly tell the King,</l>
               <l>That ſince our God hath fix'd the time, the place,</l>
               <l>And Sacrifice, we muſt with thee find grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When he perceiv'd excuſes were in vain,</l>
               <l>That obſtinacy did encreaſe his pain,</l>
               <l>The next reſolve was feign'd obedience</l>
               <l>To God and <hi>Moſes:</hi> thus, you may from hence</l>
               <l>Remove, with my free leave, if you will ſwear</l>
               <l>Not to go far, and let me quickly hear</l>
               <l>That you have begg'd of him to ſet me free,</l>
               <l>From the proud inſects all, and loathſome Flie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> reply'd. If thou do keep thy word;</l>
               <l>At thy deſire we will entreat the Lord,</l>
               <l>Who (I am ſure) will order the retreat</l>
               <l>Of theſe wing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d
troops, tho noiſome, fierce and great.</l>
               <l>To morrow they ſhall every one remove</l>
               <l>From thee and thine, thy gratitude to prove.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:48379:33"/>
               <l>The thing is done, yet <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſtill denies</l>
               <l>The people Licence to do ſacrifice.</l>
               <l>Nor Blood, nor Frogs, nor Lice, nor Flies can awe</l>
               <l>The ſtubborn Prince, nor to obedience draw</l>
               <l>His callous heart; that ſelf-deceiving cheat,</l>
               <l>Muſt be out-witted by a plague as great</l>
               <l>As any of the former. Heav'n once more</l>
               <l>Calls unto <hi>Moſes</hi> as he did before;</l>
               <l>Saying, go to the Palace and declare</l>
               <l>To him again, what my intentions are</l>
               <l>I am his, and the <hi>Hebrews</hi> God, tho he</l>
               <l>Knows not my name, nor his own deſtiny.</l>
               <l>If he refuſe to hearken to this word,</l>
               <l>I will lift up my hand, with flaming Swor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>O'er's Cattle, Horſes, Aſſes, Camels, Sheep</l>
               <l>And Oxen, which he doth in Paſtures keep.</l>
               <l>Peſtilent fogs ſhall from the earth ariſe,</l>
               <l>Malignant vapours, from the ſtarry Skies.</l>
               <l>Theſe ſhall their blood corrupt, whence putrid hearts,</l>
               <l>Shall ſcorch with piercing pains and ſhiv'ring ſweats.</l>
               <l>So that the Oxe ſhall fall beneath the yoke,</l>
               <l>The ſacrifice ſhall die before the ſtroke.</l>
               <l>The Horſe ſhall leave his prancing, and his head</l>
               <l>Shall giddy turn, run round, and fall down dead.</l>
               <l>Aſſes ſhall bray, and Camels breathe their laſt,</l>
               <l>And dizzy'd Sheep themſelves in Ditches caſt.</l>
               <l>The nimble Dogs ſhall howl, forget their meat,</l>
               <l>And teaming Ewes for pain their Breaſts will beat,</l>
               <l>All which will his unhappineſs compleat.</l>
               <l>He acts as if he knew not what I meant,</l>
               <l>This ſhall not be a gen'ral puniſhment.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:48379:34"/>His only ſhall it feel, my people's
Beaſts</l>
               <l>Muſt be exempted from theſe (carrion) Feaſts,</l>
               <l>They ſhall continue healthy, fat as ever,</l>
               <l>Mercy ſhall be the Skreen, by which I'll ſever</l>
               <l>Their Herds and Flocks from thine, that thou mayſt ſee,</l>
               <l>He muſt be loſer that oppoſeth me.</l>
               <l>All's done, and yet his heart doth harder grow,</l>
               <l>Heav'n muſt him wonders more, and greater ſhew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'If Souldiers when their Breaches open lye,</l>
               <l>'Can neither them defend nor fortify;</l>
               <l>'Do ſtill refuſe to make a fair ſurrender</l>
               <l>'On honourable terms, deſpiſe the tender</l>
               <l>'Of Lives and Arms, or what elſe is thought fit</l>
               <l>'To grant, the next reſolve is ſtorming it</l>
               <l>'With res'lute bravery, ſo that they may know</l>
               <l>From Juſtice, what they did to Mercy owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Heav'n proceeds againſt him when ſecure,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt make overture,</l>
               <l>But ſuddenly call out a fixt Brigade</l>
               <l>Of Granadiers, who ne'er yet mercy had</l>
               <l>Where Juſtice was Commander, Water, Earth,</l>
               <l>Are both too mild, the Tyrants ſettled wrath</l>
               <l>To mittigate, the fiery element</l>
               <l>Muſt act its part in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s puniſhment.</l>
               <l>I'll give no warning, Go, and Cinders take</l>
               <l>Out of the Furnace, of which you ſhall make</l>
               <l>Large Hand granado's, and them upward throw,</l>
               <l>Which kindling there ſhall aſhes turn below,</l>
               <l>Aſhes, that may breed Boils on Beaſt and Man,</l>
               <l>Then let his wiſe men cure them (if they can)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:48379:34"/>They throw, it's done, the duſty aſhes
fell,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Magi</hi> cry, we ne'er ſaw ſuch a ſpell,</l>
               <l>For they like Cauſticks ſuch Bliſters made</l>
               <l>Such Boils and Blains as <hi>Egypt</hi> never had</l>
               <l>The Sorcerers for ſhame pulled in their Creſts,</l>
               <l>Becauſe their Boils grew on their Heads, Hands, and
Breaſts,</l>
               <l>By which their Monarch might moſt plainly ſee</l>
               <l>That it was no enchantment, but decree</l>
               <l>For their deſtruction. Yet the blinded man</l>
               <l>(Acted by God) perſiſts as he began.</l>
               <l>Not mov'd by Blood, Frogs, Lice, nor Flies, nor Murrain,</l>
               <l>The Boils and Scabs do not his pride reſtrain,</l>
               <l>This angry Heav'n reſents, and gives command</l>
               <l>To <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, Early riſe, and ſtand</l>
               <l>Before the King to morrow, 'nd let him know</l>
               <l>That <hi>Jacobs</hi> God will have his Servants go</l>
               <l>To ſacrifice. Bid him look to his State,</l>
               <l>I will no more with him Capitulate,</l>
               <l>But one great plague after another ſend,</l>
               <l>Until his pride with's life is at an end,</l>
               <l>And Kingdom ruin'd, that the world may ſee,</l>
               <l>There's none on Earth, hath equal pow'r with me.</l>
               <l>The Murrain I will turn to peſtilence.</l>
               <l>That he and his may death receive from thence,</l>
               <l>His ſtubborneſs admits of no ſuſpence:</l>
               <l>My firſt plague could his pride have conquered,</l>
               <l>Second or third, but all by me forbid,</l>
               <l>Struck gently, that his caſe might warning be</l>
               <l>To all are haughty, ſtubborn, falſe as he,</l>
               <l>Each Tyrant ſhall receive this Tyrants doom,</l>
               <l>Either in this or in the world to come.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:48379:35"/>Tell him, he holds of me his Crown. His
riſe</l>
               <l>Was to inform the faithful, and the wiſe</l>
               <l>Of my great pow'r and mercy, that they may</l>
               <l>Tremble at that, and for this ever pray.</l>
               <l>Thinks he (fond man) that I can always ſee</l>
               <l>(And not redreſs) my peoples miſery?</l>
               <l>No, he ſhall find about this time to morrow</l>
               <l>The Heav'ns arm to magnify his ſorrow,</l>
               <l>Clouds dark and pregnant, fortifi'd with Thunder,</l>
               <l>A ſtormy ſhower ſhall hurl down to his wonder,</l>
               <l>Hail of ſuch unknown bigneſs and ſuch weight,</l>
               <l>As him and his, with preſent Death will fright.</l>
               <l>Bid him his Wiſe men call to aſſign the cauſe</l>
               <l>Of ſuch a rupture in great Nature's Laws.</l>
               <l>Ask if they can at once raiſe ſuch a ſhow'r,</l>
               <l>As may begin ſuch day, and end ſuch hour,</l>
               <l>And in that time ſurround th' <hi>Egyptian</hi> Coaſts,</l>
               <l>Then bid defiance to the Lord of Hoſts.</l>
               <l>Go now proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> try thy utmoſt skill,</l>
               <l>To ſave thy people from this threatned ill.</l>
               <l>If thou wilt yet be wiſe thy Cattle gather</l>
               <l>Out of the Fields, ſince thou art <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Father,</l>
               <l>Pity thy Children with their Herds and Flocks,</l>
               <l>Afford them ſhelter from the frozen Rocks,</l>
               <l>Elſe by this plague ſuch Slaughters will be ſeen</l>
               <l>Thro all thy Land as never yet hath been.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Behold the natures of the obdurate!</l>
               <l>'Tho all of them ſlight mercy, yet ill fate</l>
               <l>'Makes ſome diſtinction, fear of puniſhment,</l>
               <l>'Forceth a few into acknowledgment</l>
               <l>'Of pow'r divine, and for their ſafety cry,</l>
               <l>'Whilſt others fear'd and mad, do ſtill deny</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:48379:35"/>'Obedience to their great ſuperior,</l>
               <l>'Huſh 'twill be o'er, ſaid they, tis but a ſhower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Impending woe mov'd ſuch as yet had ſence,</l>
               <l>To view the Fields in haſte, and bring from thence</l>
               <l>Shepherds and Herdſmen, ſaying, quickly fly</l>
               <l>Home with your herds and flocks, or all muſt die.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> hath ſaid it, and we do believe</l>
               <l>That he from God, not Satan, did receive</l>
               <l>His Rod, his fearful Rod hath ſuch things done,</l>
               <l>As ſhow they were not wrought by him alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>However, we will for our ſafety try,</l>
               <l>'Tis no great trouble, if we live or dye.</l>
               <l>Others, who no regard had for his word,</l>
               <l>Said, what! <hi>Egyptians</hi> believe the Lord,</l>
               <l>Faint-hearted Fools, unworthy ſuch a King,</l>
               <l>Who laughs at all the Meſſages they bring</l>
               <l>From their fam'd Gods, our herds ſhall ſtay and graze,</l>
               <l>And ſo like men, we'll dare him to his face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Unheard of boldneſs, ſaid the Thunderer</l>
               <l>Unto his Servant, now, my mercy's ear</l>
               <l>Is ſhut for ever. Therefore lift thy hand</l>
               <l>To Heaven, I muſt ſend down a ſtarry band</l>
               <l>Of Bow-men, with ſuch Bullets as ſhall beat</l>
               <l>Out of their hearts this irreligious heat.</l>
               <l>Man, Beaſt and Herbs, thro all the Land ſhall feel</l>
               <l>The weighty Stones, the keenneſs of my Steel.</l>
               <l>Make no delay, to Heav'n thy Rod ſtretch forth,</l>
               <l>That I may ſend from the Eaſt, Weſt, South and North</l>
               <l>Thunder, and Hail, and Fire, theſe all around</l>
               <l>Shall fly aloft, and run upon the ground,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:48379:36"/>With ſo great fury, that the Waters
face</l>
               <l>Bright horrour ſhall adorn, and ev'ry place</l>
               <l>Look like it ſelf, tranſparent, as the Fire</l>
               <l>And mixed Hail, as if they were entire</l>
               <l>One body bright, yet terrible to ſee,</l>
               <l>Two el'ments joyn'd that never did agree.</l>
               <l>The Rod's lift up, then from the Clouds a voice</l>
               <l>Rendeth the Sky with ſuch a dreadful noiſe,</l>
               <l>That Earth (tho heavy) cannot longer ſtand,</l>
               <l>But reels and ſtaggers, when it feels the hand</l>
               <l>Omnipotent, who gave it its firſt baſe,</l>
               <l>It gapes and opens ſo, that there's no place</l>
               <l>For Paſture, Corn, for Cattle, Herbs and Trees,</l>
               <l>All ſink away unto their deſtinies.</l>
               <l>Only in <hi>Goſhen</hi> all-wiſe Providence</l>
               <l>Againſt this ſtorm maketh a ſtout defence.</l>
               <l>He that the troubled Ocean commands,</l>
               <l>Forbid the Hail to fall upon thoſe Lands.</l>
               <l>This unlook'd for, this great diſcrimination</l>
               <l>Betwixt th' <hi>Egyptian,</hi> and the <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Nation,</l>
               <l>Made the King ſerious, who doth now begin</l>
               <l>With forc'd expreſſions, to confeſs his ſin</l>
               <l>To <hi>Moſes</hi> and to <hi>Aaron;</hi> ſaying thus,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> is wicked, Heav'n is Righteous.</l>
               <l>Good men! entreat your God once more for me</l>
               <l>To ceaſe the Thund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rings, let the Hail ſtorm be</l>
               <l>Abated, then what you deſire I'll give,</l>
               <l>It is enough if I and mine may live.</l>
               <l>I'd better loſe ſuch Subjects than to hire</l>
               <l>Them at ſo dear a rate; they ſhall retire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To which the Prophet maketh this reply,</l>
               <l>I muſt go hence, before I lift on high.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:48379:36"/>My heart and hands for thee, unto the
Lord,</l>
               <l>That th' Hail and Thunder may ceaſe at my word,</l>
               <l>And turn to their own elements, to ſhow</l>
               <l>That th' Heav'ns above are Gods, and th' Earth below.</l>
               <l>But I am ſure when this great plague is o're,</l>
               <l>Thy thoughts will be the ſame as heretofore,</l>
               <l>Faithleſs and froward, and thy ſottiſh crew</l>
               <l>Of ſlaviſh Subjects will their rage renew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The damage done by this ſeventh plague's ſo great,</l>
               <l>That with dry Eyes no man can it repeat.</l>
               <l>The Flax now ripe, from whence the Staple trade</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Egypt</hi> had its riſe, and Linnen made,</l>
               <l>By ſubtile corruſcations withered,</l>
               <l>The pond'rous Hail its bolls (knopt off) interr'd,</l>
               <l>And bowing Barley, calling for the hand</l>
               <l>Of nimble Sythe-man, buried in the Sand.</l>
               <l>The Wheat and Rye that did not yet appear,</l>
               <l>Were only ſav'd from this great Maſſacre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'The Judgment muſt be great, all muſt confeſs,</l>
               <l>'When <hi>Eden</hi>'s turn'd into a Wilderneſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaw; but when thro <hi>Moſes</hi>'s
pray'r,</l>
               <l>The Sun diſpers'd the Clouds, and made all fair:</l>
               <l>When Thunder, Rain and Hail, were called in,</l>
               <l>He waxed worſe, and added ſin to ſin,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ill example was ſo prevalent</l>
               <l>With all his Subjects, that they likewiſe bent</l>
               <l>Their minds on future miſchief, and deny</l>
               <l>Their puniſher to pleaſe or gratify:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:48379:37"/>Who now reſolv'd on <hi>Egypt</hi>'s
deſolation,</l>
               <l>And the deliv'ry of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Nation,</l>
               <l>Said <hi>Moſes,</hi> Go unto the King, yet know</l>
               <l>That I his heart have harden'd, he'll not bow,</l>
               <l>To make my wiſdom, pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and glory ſhine,</l>
               <l>For ages after in the eyes of thine,</l>
               <l>By thy inſtruction, and may oft repeat</l>
               <l>With joy and gratitude, the wonders great</l>
               <l>For their redemption wrought, and conſtant prove</l>
               <l>To thee their Leader, me their great <hi>Jehove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Away in haſte unto the faithleſs King,</l>
               <l>And ſay, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> God remembering</l>
               <l>His Servants ſlavery, and thy peeviſhneſs,</l>
               <l>Reſolves thy ruin, this is the Expreſs:</l>
               <l>He wonders at thy refractory Spirit</l>
               <l>Which will not humble, after thy juſt merit</l>
               <l>Hath brought ſeven plagues; 'tis time his friends were
gone,</l>
               <l>The eighth is near, a great and grievous one,</l>
               <l>A dreadful hoſt ſent by a ſcorching wind</l>
               <l>From the South weſt, will eat that's left behind,</l>
               <l>That will diſrobe thy new-cloath'd Fields and Trees</l>
               <l>Of all their Summer Glories, Liveries,</l>
               <l>And ſuch a Famine bring as heretofore</l>
               <l>When <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sons to <hi>Egypt</hi> firſt came
o'er,</l>
               <l>And greater much, becauſe the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Prince,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> your Saviour is forgot long ſince,</l>
               <l>Who (like a father) furniſh'd you with Corn,</l>
               <l>When faint thro hunger you did daily mourn</l>
               <l>Before his Gate. His wiſe, his melting heart,</l>
               <l>Found out new meaſures by a divine art,</l>
               <l>That might your wants ſupply, and you relieve,</l>
               <l>Not dreaming then that you his race would grieve,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:48379:37"/>With ſtripes, diſgrace, with burthens,
and with death,</l>
               <l>Revenge implacable, and endleſs wrath.</l>
               <l>Theſe are your crimes, and this your puniſhment.</l>
               <l>To morrow Locuſts will from Heav'n be ſent;</l>
               <l>Locuſts, ſo ſtrange, ſo great, ſo numerous,</l>
               <l>They'll cover all the Land, and fill each Houſe,</l>
               <l>The Land that promis'd you a ſmall ſupply,</l>
               <l>After the Hail and Rain ſhall putrifie,</l>
               <l>The fruitful Trees ſhall ſhake their Leaves, and bare</l>
               <l>Meadows ſhall look, as Winter had been there;</l>
               <l>Whate'er proud <hi>Nile,</hi> and the attracting Sun</l>
               <l>Hath forced from the Earth ſhall be undone;</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall your Bodies from them be excus'd,</l>
               <l>Such meaſures you ſhall have as you have us'd,</l>
               <l>Your Tongues and Hands were ſharpen'd, and your Swords</l>
               <l>Deſtroy'd my people; your moſt pleaſant words</l>
               <l>Like Serpents, Vipers, and like Waſps did bite,</l>
               <l>The fainting, feeble, famiſht <hi>Iſraelite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their poyſon'd ſtings ſhall pierce your trembling
veins,</l>
               <l>Opening their Sluces, as you did the Drains</l>
               <l>Thro <hi>Nile</hi>'s great banks, to vex my Servants hearts,</l>
               <l>That when you feel the fury of their Darts,</l>
               <l>You may bind up, not chaff the wound that ſmarts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This when the angry Prophet had expreſt,</l>
               <l>Without farewel, he leaves him, and the reſt</l>
               <l>Unſpoken—All his Counſellors diſmaid,</l>
               <l>Seeing <hi>Moſes</hi> to their King no reverence paid</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:48379:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>At his departure, but with high
diſdain,</l>
               <l>Show'd by his looks, charg'd him once more on pain</l>
               <l>Of Death in haſte to let the people go,</l>
               <l>Cry, 'tis of God, now we muſt own it ſo,</l>
               <l>We muſt ſubmit unto their God's decree,</l>
               <l>And not of our own ruin authors be.</l>
               <l>Tho we could flatter when all things went well,</l>
               <l>We muſt give over now, and frankly tell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>The King that he, not we, began this
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>In which we're daily worſted, better far</l>
               <l>It is to yield, than wait th' unknown event,</l>
               <l>We ſee their Magazines cannot be ſpent.</l>
               <l>They are not men we fight with, when the pow'rs</l>
               <l>Of Heav'n and Earth are raiſed, what are ours?</l>
               <l>A loathſome Louſe, a Frog, a Flie can bring</l>
               <l>Deſtruction on us, and on our King.</l>
               <l>Come, lets not dally; here! the Monarch comes</l>
               <l>Chaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with the late
affront, he ſtares, he foams,</l>
               <l>Who dares accoſt him in this furious mood?</l>
               <l>His trembling ſhows the thirſteth after blood.</l>
               <l>But we muſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y
before it be too late</l>
               <l>With him about this matter to debate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Sir, our grief, not boldneſs, makes us offer</l>
               <l>The Nations ſtate, our troubles will not ſuffer</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onger connivance,
ſpeedy remedy</l>
               <l>Muſt be conſulted on 'twixt us and thee.</l>
               <l>Earth, Water, Fire and Air do all agree,</l>
               <l>(Againſt our Counſels) to ſet <hi>Iſrael</hi> free:</l>
               <l>It muſt be done, neceſſity hath no Law,</l>
               <l>Pray Sir be wiſe, and let the men withdraw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:48379:38"/>
               <l>My Lords, it is not ſtrange that loſs and fear,</l>
               <l>Give you occaſion to accoſt my ear</l>
               <l>With ſuch ſurprizing Language. But I wonder</l>
               <l>That <hi>Jannes, Jambres,</hi> who ſo oft did Thunder</l>
               <l>Another Dialect, ſhould cringe and truckle</l>
               <l>Againſt the rules of their own art, and buckle</l>
               <l>To foreign fancies. Yet it grieves me moſt</l>
               <l>That this grave Prieſt ſhould too himſelf be loſt,</l>
               <l>Who <hi>Pharaoh</hi> wiſhed the fondling brat to kill,</l>
               <l>His Daughters joy, before he had done ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All made returns, the mighty Lords begin.</l>
               <l>Great Sir, the loſs is yours, we would not ſin</l>
               <l>Againſt a Prince ſo glorious, ſo great,</l>
               <l>Againſt a fertile Land, and potent State,</l>
               <l>Of all we muſt be guilty, if we do</l>
               <l>Our eyes hoodwink, our ſenſes, brains forego.</l>
               <l>It is the glory of a Courtier</l>
               <l>Firſt to foreſee, and then prevent the ſhower;</l>
               <l>This is our Province, time loſt to recover</l>
               <l>Is full of hazard. Pray, Great Sir give over.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sorcerers in order next appear,</l>
               <l>Bluſhing with ſhame, and ſtupifi'd with fear,</l>
               <l>Dread Soveraign (ſay they) our mortal ſtate</l>
               <l>Admits of changes, while this grand debate</l>
               <l>'Twixt Heav'n and you lay dormant, our Ally's</l>
               <l>Taught us both God and Men how to deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>You, you, great Sir, excepted, now they flie,</l>
               <l>They dare not ape Heav'ns ſmalleſt prodigy,</l>
               <l>Nor us encourage you to gratify.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:48379:39"/>
               <l>The aged Father laſt of all comes forth,</l>
               <l>With Mitred head, gray hairs of famed worth,</l>
               <l>Who ſaid, O King! your great experience</l>
               <l>Of my fidelity, and vaſt expence,</l>
               <l>Deſerves of you a better recompence.</l>
               <l>I told that King before the Child was born,</l>
               <l>That he would be the cauſe of <hi>Egypt</hi>'s ſcorn,</l>
               <l>If then his Death by him had been decreed,</l>
               <l>As I requeſted, <hi>Egypt</hi> had been freed</l>
               <l>From all theſe plagues. For he himſelf preſaged</l>
               <l>In Childiſh ſports, what he would do when aged.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his Infant Temples did adorn</l>
               <l>With <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Crown, which he pull'd off in ſcorn,</l>
               <l>By which moſt juſt ſuſpicion he gave,</l>
               <l>That he would force the Sceptre, not receive</l>
               <l>It from his hands. Then, it was my advice,</l>
               <l>That death ſhould pay him for the enterprize.</l>
               <l>But now 't's too late, he's King, you his Viceroy,</l>
               <l>Which (I forſee) you will not long enjoy,</l>
               <l>He threatens, kills, commands, and which is more,</l>
               <l>Deſtroys our Lands, their Fruits, and all our ſtore,</l>
               <l>There is but one way left us to preſerve</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egyyt</hi> from ruin, that we may not ſtarve,</l>
               <l>To let them go, that they may ſerve the Lord,</l>
               <l>Perhaps this <hi>Moſes</hi> may perform his word.</l>
               <l>He ſays Heav'n's merciful, and will repent,</l>
               <l>Of his fierce anger, if ill men relent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You have o'rcome me, ſaid the raging King,</l>
               <l>Go out in haſte, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>
bring.</l>
               <l>A Monarch is no Monarch when alone,</l>
               <l>(His Subjects ruin'd) let the men be gone,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:48379:39"/>To do as they have ſaid, yet I muſt
ſee</l>
               <l>Th' extent of this great Goal-delivery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> Heav'n's fury acted by thy hand,</l>
               <l>I am no longer able to withſtand.</l>
               <l>Tell me, but who muſt go? Let modeſty</l>
               <l>Bound your demands, and they ſhall granted be,</l>
               <l>Who asks too much his own denyal craves,</l>
               <l>I will not part at once with all my Slaves.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You are not ignorant, great Sir, I know</l>
               <l>By this time, that my Meſſage from below</l>
               <l>Came not, juſt Heaven me often did command</l>
               <l>The Tribes to carry out of <hi>Egypt</hi>'s land,</l>
               <l>And they muſt go Men, Children, Herds and Sheep,</l>
               <l>None muſt be abſent, when our Feaſts we keep</l>
               <l>Unto <hi>Jehovah</hi>—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is this the juſtice of your fam'd <hi>Jehove?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is this the kindneſs of your God of love</l>
               <l>To his Vicegerents? ſaid the angry King,</l>
               <l>Muſt they ſubmit to every idle thing</l>
               <l>That he requires? Muſt every Slave have power</l>
               <l>To ſpoil their goods, and honours to deflow'r?</l>
               <l>No, this great point I will diſpute and try,</l>
               <l>Who muſt be here obeyed he or I,</l>
               <l>Your little ones as pledges I will keep</l>
               <l>Till you return, Go you with Herds and Sheep,</l>
               <l>If this will not content you, look you to it,</l>
               <l>I'll puniſh you with ſtripes and Death to boot,</l>
               <l>The preſent loſſes I thro you ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>My honour ſhall repair, which I'll regain,</l>
               <l>By conqu'ring him, in you his Subjects ſlain,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:48379:40"/>Go then I ſay, and let your Children
ſtay.</l>
               <l>What! Murmur? Serjeants drive the fools away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The General omnipotent, who far</l>
               <l>Or near, ne'er yet made one falſe ſtep in War,</l>
               <l>Laugh'd at the indiſcretion of his foe,</l>
               <l>And ſaid to his Lieutenant, you muſt go</l>
               <l>With new rais'd Troops to curb the inſolence</l>
               <l>Of this unwary, this bewitched Prince,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Eurus</hi> be the Trumpeter, whoſe breath</l>
               <l>Shall animate the Army, threatning Death,</l>
               <l>Death unto Men and Beaſts, that they may ſee</l>
               <l>I do demand this Goal-delivery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſpoke no ſooner than he was obey'd</l>
               <l>The hand is ſtretched forth, and Rod diſplay'd</l>
               <l>O'er <hi>Egypt</hi> Land, then the Eaſt Wind doth call</l>
               <l>The Catterpillers, Locuſts, Inſects all,</l>
               <l>Out of their ſlimy duſt, who buz and fly</l>
               <l>About the ears of every ſtander by,</l>
               <l>Seizing on all the Fruits they could deſtroy.</l>
               <l>The Earth was cover'd with the numerous ſwarms,</l>
               <l>No Tree, no Fruit, no Herb, eſcap't their harms,</l>
               <l>Their Eyes, their Mouths, their Stings were mercileſs,</l>
               <l>This made the Prince with tears, his grief expreſs</l>
               <l>Unto the Brethren, with heart-breaking voice,</l>
               <l>I cannot longer hear this dreadful noiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'O! that Heav'n had not brought me to the Throne,</l>
               <l>'O! that I'd Hermit been, and liv'd alone</l>
               <l>'In unfrequented Groves, in Woods and Caves,</l>
               <l>'Careleſs of Crowns, Lands, Subjects, or of Slaves.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:48379:40"/>'If Heav'n had been my Canopy, my Bed</l>
               <l>'The Flow'ry Earth, the Pillow for my Head</l>
               <l>'A bundle of Vi'lets, Pinks or Cammomile,</l>
               <l>'Roſe-buds with Lillies, and ſweat ſmelling Dill;</l>
               <l>'My meat wild Fruits, with quinteſſence of Bees,</l>
               <l>'My Drink ſweet Liquors from the juicy Trees;</l>
               <l>'My recreation hunting of the Hare,</l>
               <l>'The vacant hours I could from Study ſpare,</l>
               <l>'Or Fox or Deer, or what I liked beſt,</l>
               <l>'I had not then by Heav'n been thus oppreſt:</l>
               <l>'But ſo <hi>Jehove</hi> would have it, he did raiſe</l>
               <l>'Me to this ſhame, for his immortal praiſe,</l>
               <l>'That Kings may learn true wiſdom, and their Subjects</l>
               <l>'Dread ev'n in thought, ſuch great, ſuch fearful
objects,</l>
               <l>'As high ambition, Diabolick pride</l>
               <l>'Will bring on all, like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſtupifi'd,</l>
               <l>'My hainous crimes and grievous puniſhment</l>
               <l>'Will fright the worſt, and force them to repent,</l>
               <l>'As I begin (O! may't not be too late)</l>
               <l>'I grieve, I mourn, Alas!—my curſed fate</l>
               <l>'Made me offend your God, his Sons and you,</l>
               <l>'For which I pardon crave with tears and vow,</l>
               <l>'My Life I ſee is threat'ned, yet ſpare</l>
               <l>'This once, that I may ſee what's mercies are;</l>
               <l>'Forgive, forgive, my friends, and you ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>'That weeping <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will not falſify.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> the God-like <hi>Moſes,</hi> judg'd his
heart</l>
               <l>By his expreſſions, knew no wheedling art,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Sympathy with tears made him depart,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:48379:41"/>And thus accoſt his maker, I have
prov'd</l>
               <l>The King, who begs this plague may be remov'd</l>
               <l>At my requeſt, my God, let it be ſo</l>
               <l>Since he hath vowed that the men ſhall go</l>
               <l>Without delay, yet be that as it will,</l>
               <l>Omnipotence hath Armies that can kill,</l>
               <l>As theſe have done ſuch wonders, more, when ſhown,</l>
               <l>The more men will thy Juſtice, Mercy own.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It ſhall be done, I'll call a Weſtern Wind</l>
               <l>Shall clear the Land, (tho you him falfe will find)</l>
               <l>That all thoſe living Clouds ſhall headlong bear</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Arabick</hi> watry Sepulcher,</l>
               <l>Whoſe purple waves will quickly overflow,</l>
               <l>And ſend them to the fiſh that dwell below,</l>
               <l>A Feaſt that heretofore they did not know:</l>
               <l>I will not leave one Locuſt on his Coaſts,</l>
               <l>That he may know I am the Lord of Hoſts.</l>
               <l>This done, the Hypocrite forgets his woe,</l>
               <l>His ſolemn vow, and will not let them go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaid God, the blindneſs of this man,</l>
               <l>Hath ſtill encreaſed ſince the War began</l>
               <l>With us, ſince wonders will not ope his eyes,</l>
               <l>The Sun, the Moon, the Air, ſhall him deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Stretch out thy Rod to Heav'n and damp the Fires,</l>
               <l>Give light and heat to th' Earth, and mens deſires</l>
               <l>With pleaſure gratify, and let no Star</l>
               <l>Our En'mies guide, it is a time of War,</l>
               <l>Make the Air thick and black, for three days ſpace,</l>
               <l>That none of them may ſee anothers face,</l>
               <l>But fixed ſit, not riſing from his place,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:48379:41"/>Yet let my Servants have their wonted
joy,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Goſhen</hi> light to ſee, that I employ</l>
               <l>My wiſdom, power, and juſtice, arm'd with might</l>
               <l>On their behalf, that they're my hearts delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Day put's on mourning, the night birds appear</l>
               <l>At noon, the Hemiſphere wax'd black with fear,</l>
               <l>Thinking that <hi>Phoebus</hi> would come no more there.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cynthia</hi> (for ſhame) creepeth behind the Earth,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> weeping, ceaſe to
breath</l>
               <l>Their flaming Vapours, all the reſt do wrap</l>
               <l>Their drowſie heads in troubled <hi>Thetis</hi>'s lap.</l>
               <l>Thouſands of terrours thro the darkneſs fled,</l>
               <l>The Ghoſts complain'd, the Spirits murmured,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Egypt</hi> (like the damn'd) did howl and cry,</l>
               <l>For glo'worm-light, which Heaven doth them deny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This made the King again for <hi>Moſes</hi> call,</l>
               <l>Say'ng you may go, your little ones and all,</l>
               <l>Except your Flocks and Herds, they muſt remain</l>
               <l>With me in ſafety till you come again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Ah! <hi>Moſes, Moſes,</hi> was not thou the boy;</l>
               <l>'Drawn out of <hi>Nile</hi> to be the Princeſs joy</l>
               <l>'In Flaggen boat? Did not that King paſs by</l>
               <l>'Thy Childiſh faults, and crimes of deeper dye.</l>
               <l>'Of all his Armies thou waſt General;</l>
               <l>'Peer unto him and Daughter, dear to all,</l>
               <l>'All was committed to thy prudent care,</l>
               <l>'Then be not, be not executioner</l>
               <l>'To their ſucceſſor.—ſpeak yet to thy friend,</l>
               <l>Whoſe mercies (as you ſay) do never end,</l>
               <l>Your Cattle leaving for my proper uſe,</l>
               <l>The reſt may go, I will no more refuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:48379:42"/>
               <l>Sir, your fair promiſe would prevail with me,</l>
               <l>If I was Maſter of my Liberty.</l>
               <l>When I was baniſh'd firſt from <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Court,</l>
               <l>I with my Flocks to <hi>Horeb</hi> did reſort,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horeb,</hi> much fam'd for Spirits habitation,</l>
               <l>I choſe for paſture and for meditation,</l>
               <l>Where I continued, till one Summer-day</l>
               <l>I ſought a Sheep that from the reſt did ſtray</l>
               <l>Amongſt the Thickets, one of which did ſhow</l>
               <l>Like Flames above, and yet unburn'd below,</l>
               <l>A voice from thence came to my trembling ear,</l>
               <l>Which (I am ſure) ſaid <hi>Moſes,</hi> come not near,</l>
               <l>The place where thou doſt ſtand is holy ground,</l>
               <l>This double wonder caſt me in a ſwound,</l>
               <l>From which reviv'd, appeared to my ſight</l>
               <l>A form divine, than Cherubin more bright,</l>
               <l>With charming Language, ſuch as Seraphs uſe</l>
               <l>In courting Mortals, who by craft refuſe</l>
               <l>Heav'ns favours, and the beſt inheritance.</l>
               <l>By this rouz'd up I made a ſmall advance,</l>
               <l>Whom he perceiving, readily did meet,</l>
               <l>And (with a Godlike ſmile) thus did me greet.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> born, thou know'ſt it
well,</l>
               <l>Its King, and all the Strangers in it dwell,</l>
               <l>They're mine, tho poor, afflicted and diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>That King and people have them long oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Thou muſt be firſt Ambaſſador, then Guide,</l>
               <l>To bring them over to the other ſide</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Jordan.</hi>—Great Sir; this was my
Commiſſion,</l>
               <l>I muſt not alter it without permiſſion.</l>
               <l>Pray urge no more, this is a fond device</l>
               <l>Without our Flocks, we cannot Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>Nor offerings make. It is <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s mind,</l>
               <l>That we in <hi>Egypt</hi> leave no hoof behind,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:48379:42"/>This general command we muſt obey;</l>
               <l>Yet know not when we come, what he will ſay</l>
               <l>Unto us more. Devotion chiefly tends</l>
               <l>To Heav'n's praiſe, with many other ends,</l>
               <l>Unknown to thee.—</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The more I do comply, the more I treat</l>
               <l>In love and calmneſs, your new zeal and he at</l>
               <l>Encreaſeth, I muſt leave the whole debate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> be gone, look to thy ſelf, if I</l>
               <l>Again behold thy face, thou'rt ſure to die.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt well ſpoken, this is Prophecy,</l>
               <l>For one act more compleats thy Tragedy;</l>
               <l>A plague to which the reſt ſhall ſeem but ſmall,</l>
               <l>Shall not upon thy Flocks and Cattle fall</l>
               <l>Alone, as heretofore, but ſhall deſtroy</l>
               <l>The oldeſt pledges of your loves and joy.</l>
               <l>This for a time ſhall move thy ſtubborn heart,</l>
               <l>To favour <hi>Iſra'l,</hi> force them to depart,</l>
               <l>And when reſiſtance thou ſhalt after make,</l>
               <l>What the Sword leaves, the foaming Sea ſhall take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Know then, proud King, when all are faſt aſleep,</l>
               <l>This night, when thee thy doubled Guards do keep,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Michael,</hi> fam'd for ſtrength and warlike power,</l>
               <l>By Heav'n's warrant, ſhall break ope each door</l>
               <l>In thy unhallow'd Country, and ſhall kill</l>
               <l>From <hi>Egypt</hi>'s heir, that next the Throne ſhould
fill,</l>
               <l>To hers that grindeth in the <hi>Bridewel</hi> Mill,</l>
               <l>None of the firſt-born ſhall alive remain</l>
               <l>Of Men, of Women, Beaſts, all ſhall be ſlain,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:48379:43"/>Whoſe dying ſhrieks and groans ſhall
pierce thy Soul,</l>
               <l>And make their frighted Parents cry and howl,</l>
               <l>Unheard of woes thy fearful heart ſhall ſeize,</l>
               <l>While they in <hi>Goſhen</hi> live in health and eaſe,</l>
               <l>Each of their doors ſhall have a Centinel,</l>
               <l>The grand deſtroyers hand that my repel.</l>
               <l>The Crimſon'd Poſts and Lintels ſhall reveal</l>
               <l>Heav'ns ſecret will to him that bears the Steel.</l>
               <l>When thou doſt ſee this great diſcrimination</l>
               <l>Betwixt the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> Nation,</l>
               <l>Thy Menaces thou will repent, and ſend</l>
               <l>The beſt of all thy ſubjects, who will bend</l>
               <l>To me and ſay, be gone with all ye have,</l>
               <l>To whom I'll anſwer; Now, no leave I crave,</l>
               <l>But in deſpite of you, and of your King,</l>
               <l>At Heav'n's command, we will make offering,</l>
               <l>Do what thou canſt, I'll ſee thy face no more,</l>
               <l>The Death thou threat'neſt is at thy own door,</l>
               <l>Thy harden'd heart Heav'n's hand will quickly break,</l>
               <l>When he on thee, and thine doth vengeance take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Ah! <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> what a diſmal change is this?</l>
               <l>'Muſt I deprived be of all my bliſs?</l>
               <l>'Upbraided, ſcorn'd, and ſlighted by a Slave,</l>
               <l>'Who holds his life of me, yet doth behave</l>
               <l>'As King o'er us, and all we have?</l>
               <l>'My feeble Gods, whoſe Altars I have ſmoak't</l>
               <l>'With beſt Perfumes, your Deities invok't,</l>
               <l>'Why ſtand you gazing on my miſery?</l>
               <l>'Hath a poor Shepherd greater pow'r than ye?</l>
               <l>'And you, infernal Spirits, whoſe great boaſts,</l>
               <l>'Perſwaded me there was no Lord of Hoſts,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:48379:43"/>'Have you no Philtre, no Enchanted
Spell,</l>
               <l>'Or is there no experiment in Hell,</l>
               <l>'Againſt this <hi>Moſes,</hi> and againſt his Rod,</l>
               <l>'Alas! I fear you think there is a God;</l>
               <l>'If ſo, I am undone, I'll not ſubmit,</l>
               <l>'Deſtruction is the worſt can come of it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this time night, the dreadful night drew on,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Egypt</hi>'s firſt-born's execution.</l>
               <l>An Angel thro the Air came flying down,</l>
               <l>With ſpeedy wing o'r <hi>Egypt</hi>'s <hi>Memphis</hi>
Town,</l>
               <l>Who without ſight or noiſe, view'd all the Tow'rs</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s lofty houſe, and's Subjects Bow'rs;</l>
               <l>Finds out the Victims, and on them doth try,</l>
               <l>The keenneſs of his Sword, by which they die,</l>
               <l>And dying, with their groans do pierce the Sky,</l>
               <l>For each, his eldeſt Child ſaw gaſping out</l>
               <l>Its tender Soul, with blood which flew about,</l>
               <l>From Wound, and Mouth, and Noſtrils with great pain,</l>
               <l>And heard their cries to Heav'n for help in vain,</l>
               <l>This made a doleful ſound o'er <hi>Egypt</hi>'s plain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'<hi>Rachel</hi> mourn'd not ſo long, ſo loud as they;</l>
               <l>'When <hi>Benjamin</hi> to his en'mies was a prey,</l>
               <l>'Nor when the Fox her Children all did ſlay;</l>
               <l>'To theirs the mourning in <hi>Megiddo</hi>'s vale,</l>
               <l>'For good <hi>Joſiah</hi> was no parallel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ev'ry Houſe ſobb'd out the ſame complaint,</l>
               <l>My eldeſt's dead! ne'er was ſuch puniſhment:</l>
               <l>The King himſelf awak'd with this alarm,</l>
               <l>Cry'd out, O Heav'n! hath this deſtroyer's arm,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:48379:44"/>Bereav'd me of my Succeſſor in
State,</l>
               <l>I ſee I muſt repent when 'tis too late,</l>
               <l>Let none (like me) again with Heav'n debate.</l>
               <l>Call in the Brothers quickly, (tho 'tis night)</l>
               <l>They ſhall go hence before next morning light;</l>
               <l>With Flocks and Herds, and all they can deſire,</l>
               <l>For which great favour I will nought require,</l>
               <l>But faithful pray'rs to God for me and mine,</l>
               <l>Who knows? He may repent, his ear incline</l>
               <l>To pity me, and haſte his own deſign?</l>
               <l>This heard, his Subjects all do beg and pray</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> to haſten <hi>Iſrael</hi> away.</l>
               <l>Haſte, haſte, ſay they, if any thing you lack,</l>
               <l>We're readier to give than you're to take,</l>
               <l>Our lives are more to us than what we give,</l>
               <l>When you are gone, we and our Babes may live.</l>
               <l>This (like melodious Muſick to thier ears)</l>
               <l>Warm'd their chill'd blood, and baniſh'd all their fears,</l>
               <l>They had full wages for four hundred years.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſignal given, our torn and helpleſs crew</l>
               <l>(Like forward ſpring) their Liveries renew,</l>
               <l>And furniſh'd with new garments, and their Slaves,</l>
               <l>Bid them farewel. Their Victuals dreſt to halves.</l>
               <l>Yet their old foes enrag'd to ſee them go,</l>
               <l>(Tho with conſent) ſaid, it muſt not be ſo.</l>
               <l>Now we are miſerable! what have we done?</l>
               <l>The Slaves with all our Treaſures hence are gone.</l>
               <l>Good news to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who a Council calls,</l>
               <l>Saying, my friends, we muſt find Generals,</l>
               <l>Horſes and Chariots, Men and Ammunition</l>
               <l>In haſte, you know th' intended expedition.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:48379:44"/>My eyes are open'd, I cannot behold</l>
               <l>Thoſe Slaves enriched with our Cloaths and Gold,</l>
               <l>They took and wear, they
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re Trophies of our Shame</l>
               <l>And Cowardice, which very things to name</l>
               <l>Are worſe than death to him, whom Gods above</l>
               <l>Nor men below, could ever yet remove</l>
               <l>From his intended purpoſes till now,</l>
               <l>Of which the reaſon yet I do not know,</l>
               <l>Heav'n (ſure) 's appeaſed ſince I've let them go.</l>
               <l>Tho I perceive, they have no mind to leave</l>
               <l>My borders while they've paid for what they have.</l>
               <l>Their God repents him of the Violence</l>
               <l>Offer'd to us before they went from hence;</l>
               <l>This makes them go about, and not purſue</l>
               <l>The beaten roads they heretofore well knew;</l>
               <l>When they for Corn to <hi>Egypt</hi> came, and when</l>
               <l>With <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Corps they back return'd agen.</l>
               <l>Their late rebellion proves to them a ſnare,</l>
               <l>Since they a lazy unarm'd people are,</l>
               <l>They cannot fight, their flight we need not fear.</l>
               <l>Up, let us follow, and cut off their Rear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dread Sir, ſaid they, your thoughts were always great,</l>
               <l>Nor Gods, nor men, your courage could abate,</l>
               <l>Pray be advis'd before this enterprize</l>
               <l>You undertake, leſt you prove after-wiſe.</l>
               <l>In vain you ſought to hinder them when here,</l>
               <l>And we your ſubjects all about you were.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:48379:45"/>Our threats, our blows, and what we could
invent,</l>
               <l>Wrought for their good, and for our puniſhment,</l>
               <l>Heav'n always doth protect the innocent.</l>
               <l>Behold the ruins of your ſhatter'd ſtate,</l>
               <l>The murder'd Heirs of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſmall and great.</l>
               <l>Think on the threatnings you did calmly bear,</l>
               <l>Think on your darling off-ſpring, then declare</l>
               <l>What hopes you have to catch them in a ſnare,</l>
               <l>Their God's the ſame, their Leader conſtant, wiſe,</l>
               <l>Therefore, great Sir, leave off this enterprize,</l>
               <l>It will prove fatal, if our dream be true;</l>
               <l>Laſt night, O King! we ſaw our ſelves with you</l>
               <l>In warlike poſture, following the men</l>
               <l>We lately forc't to go from us, and then</l>
               <l>We likewiſe ſaw Heav'n open'd, whence came down</l>
               <l>An Hoſt moſt terrible 'bout <hi>Succoth</hi> Town,</l>
               <l>Of Giant ſtature, and of ſtern aſpect,</l>
               <l>Who ſeem'd their Swords to brandiſh, and direct</l>
               <l>To our proud Throats, while we did ſtupid ſtand,</l>
               <l>Not daring to reſiſt, move tongue nor hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Away with dreams! haſte, up and let us ſhow</l>
               <l>Our ſelves Heav'ns rivals, and his peoples too.</l>
               <l>'Tis now or never that we muſt attack</l>
               <l>The wand'ring Slaves; and kill or bring them back,</l>
               <l>Their God himſelf (it ſeems) doth them forſake;</l>
               <l>Their way was ſmooth and ſhort, nor Seas, nor Rocks,</l>
               <l>Could ſtop the paſſage of themſelves or Flocks,</l>
               <l>But miſſing that, they have no way to 'ſcape,</l>
               <l>The Hills they cannot climb, nor o'er Seas leap,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:48379:45"/>That are before them, Wilderneſs and
Rocks</l>
               <l>On each ſide, we behind, whoſe deadly ſtrokes</l>
               <l>Will ſoon reduce them to their Slavery,</l>
               <l>Since they can neither fight, nor from us fly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, they mount their Chariots in haſte,</l>
               <l>The Horſe and Infantry ſcarce take repaſt,</l>
               <l>Who by their doubled marches ſoon o'ertake</l>
               <l>The ftighted <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe hearts began to ake,</l>
               <l>Together run in heaps, like fearful Sheep</l>
               <l>Attack'd by Dogs or Wolves, (when thoſe ſhould keep</l>
               <l>Are either abſent, or are faſt aſleep;</l>
               <l>Who pat and ſtare, the harmleſs dialect</l>
               <l>Of their juſt fear, as if that would effect</l>
               <l>Their reſcue—So the Tribes with direful tone</l>
               <l>Cry unto God and <hi>Moſes</hi> (whom they ſtone)</l>
               <l>Would both of you had let us ſtill alone</l>
               <l>To ſerve in <hi>Egypt,</hi> then if we had dy'd</l>
               <l>We might like men have there been bury'd,</l>
               <l>Whereas we muſt be drowned now or ſlain,</l>
               <l>We will beg pardon, and return again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> who all this time was griev'd to ſee</l>
               <l>The peoples rudeneſs, infidelity,</l>
               <l>Doth firſt expoſtulate, and then entreat</l>
               <l>Them to forbear their blaſphemy and heat,</l>
               <l>And wait with patience a ſucceſsful end</l>
               <l>Of all their troubles. What if you be penn'd</l>
               <l>Up in this Creek? What tho the Rocks and Waves</l>
               <l>Conſpire your death? What if theſe Hell-born Slaves</l>
               <l>Reſolve your future thraldom and your Death?</l>
               <l>Shakeoff all fear, there's hope as long as breath.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:48379:46"/>'Twas Heav'n that brought you hither, and
not I,</l>
               <l>To ſhow his pow'r in your delivery,</l>
               <l>Which you ſhould not diſtruſt, but magnify,</l>
               <l>Since he is faithful, who hath promiſed,</l>
               <l>And by this work will ſhow that you are freed</l>
               <l>Beyond your expectation. Stand but ſtill,</l>
               <l>Whatever <hi>Pharaoh</hi> thinks, it is Gods will</l>
               <l>That you eſcape this danger, and your foes,</l>
               <l>The outmoſt feel of their (late) feared woes.</l>
               <l>Stand ſtill. Heaven bids me ſay, you have no cauſe</l>
               <l>To grieve, they muſt ſubmit unto his Laws,</l>
               <l>While you look on, and with triumphant Tongues</l>
               <l>Sing his due praiſe, who hath redreſs'd your wrongs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All ſilent, and the Prophet gone to pray,</l>
               <l>Heav'ns hears, commands, that <hi>Iſra'l</hi> make his way</l>
               <l>Unto the foamy ſhore, where they muſt ſtand</l>
               <l>Fearleſs, and wait the ebb, when <hi>Moſes</hi>'s hand</l>
               <l>Shall ſmite the Waves, and bid them bare the Sand,</l>
               <l>To make a way pal'd on each ſide with glaſs,</l>
               <l>On which the fainting Tribes might ſafely paſs,</l>
               <l>Beyond the reach of any Enemy</l>
               <l>May them infeſt, or make diſcovery</l>
               <l>Of their night-march, until it was too late,</l>
               <l>With God or <hi>Moſes</hi> friendſhip to create,</l>
               <l>Who will behonour'd on all thoſe that know</l>
               <l>Him, or ſhall read of this great overthrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:48379:46"/>
               <l>They move, th' <hi>Egyptians</hi> laugh and ſay aloud,</l>
               <l>We thought the <hi>Hebrews</hi> God had underſtood</l>
               <l>What was moſt proper for his peoples good;</l>
               <l>But now we plainly ſee they're led by chance,</l>
               <l>Which cannot work their wiſh'd deliverance,</l>
               <l>They're ſafe enough.—Halt, let the Infantry</l>
               <l>Refreſh themſelves, and ſing the Victory,</l>
               <l>To morrow will be ſoon enough to drive</l>
               <l>The fools into the Sea; or keep alive</l>
               <l>Such as will quarter crave, and ſay, they are</l>
               <l>(At our diſpoſal) Priſoners of war.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Arms grounded, the Horſes Provender</l>
               <l>Eat, Chariots ſerve for Tents in ſudden War,</l>
               <l>Where they betook themſelves to free repoſe,</l>
               <l>And did conclude, tho Heav'n was to diſpoſe</l>
               <l>Of both the Armies, who his Angel ſent</l>
               <l>To guards his friends when thro the Sea they went,</l>
               <l>By ſpreading of a dark and diſmal Cloud</l>
               <l>O'er <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Hoſt, while lighted Torches ſtood,</l>
               <l>By the tranſparent walls to fright the Flood,</l>
               <l>And light his Servants to the other ſhore,</l>
               <l>That they might ſee their enemies no more</l>
               <l>Alive.—The ſign giv'n, Heav'n rais'd the wind,</l>
               <l>That made the Sea contract it ſelf, and bind</l>
               <l>Its furious waves, that they might not o'erflow</l>
               <l>The Walls above, nor the new way below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſra'l</hi> trod ſafe, th' <hi>Egyptians</hi>
purſue,</l>
               <l>Nor knowing where they were till morning dew</l>
               <l>Was by the Sun exhal'd, and they o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erthrew.</l>
               <l>The Foot and Horſe ſink in the ſlimy Sands,</l>
               <l>The Chariots caſt their Wheels, the Riders hands</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:48379:47"/>Were feeble, when they ſaw themſelves
ſurrounded</l>
               <l>By th' impetuous Ocean that rebounded</l>
               <l>With ſwelling, forc't by Thunder and by Rain,</l>
               <l>While they ſought to retire, but all in vain,</l>
               <l>Heav'n fights for them; ſaid they, why ſhould we
ſtrive</l>
               <l>Againſt the ſtream? Is <hi>Pharaoh</hi> yet alive?</l>
               <l>He was the author of this Tragedy.</l>
               <l>Oh! dye we muſt, we cannot longer flie</l>
               <l>Vengeance Divine, which we have juſtly brought</l>
               <l>Upon our ſelves, and this deſtruction wrought:</l>
               <l>Winds have no ears, the Seas are mercileſs,</l>
               <l>When Heav'n by Men or Angels ſends th' expreſs.</l>
               <l>Farewel dear <hi>Egypt,</hi> farewel happineſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Let Tyrants tremble where my pen relates</l>
               <l>'Th' Almighty's fury, and th' <hi>Egyptian</hi> fates.</l>
               <l>'They fight, he wards, till that unhappy war</l>
               <l>'Wax'd ſo intenſe that juſtice could not ſpare.</l>
               <l>'Small parties foil'd, he call'd the <hi>Arieaban,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Armies too fierce, too numerous for man,</l>
               <l>'The Serpent leads the Van. Their waters fry</l>
               <l>'Themſelves in blood, and took its crimſon dye,</l>
               <l>'Blood, that their Streams with ſtench did putrify,</l>
               <l>'The drowſy Inſects all ſtrong poyſon ſpeak,</l>
               <l>'Frogs haunt the Palace as the watry creek.</l>
               <l>'Lice there without an optick might be ſeen</l>
               <l>'On the Kings Carpets, and the Peaſants Skreen.</l>
               <l>'The myſtie Clouds forbad the healthful Sun,</l>
               <l>'Sucking their poyſon while the work was done.</l>
               <l>'He likewiſe bluſht to ſee the inſolence</l>
               <l>'Offer'd to wiſdom and omnipotence.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:48379:47"/>'The Stars danc'd up into a higher
ſphere,</l>
               <l>'To bath themſelves in the Cryſtal waters there.</l>
               <l>'Hell ſtorm'd the lower orbs, and left its hue</l>
               <l>'Black as <hi>Egyptian,</hi> and then withdrew.</l>
               <l>'At laſt a Prince of great fidelity</l>
               <l>'In Heav'ns guards, the firſt Majeſtick high,</l>
               <l>'With vailed face, his humble honours made</l>
               <l>'To his adored Soveraign thus ſaid.</l>
               <l>'Holy of Holies, 'tis your patience</l>
               <l>'Procures you all this trouble and expence.</l>
               <l>'Give me command, and this great debate</l>
               <l>'Shall ſoon be ended with their firſt born's fate.</l>
               <l>'Your pow'r, my hand, the Rebels ſeed ſhall kill,</l>
               <l>'As they the infant blood of yours did ſpill.</l>
               <l>'He goes with armed Peſtilence and Sword,</l>
               <l>'Two edged, ſharp, for both were Heav'n's word,</l>
               <l>'And ſmote the firſt of all their Beaſts and Men,</l>
               <l>'The ſottiſh crew (too late) believed then.</l>
               <l>'So Heav'n would have't, that by this overthrow</l>
               <l>'Of theirs a falſe preſumptuous world might know</l>
               <l>'That firſt or laſt he would proud mortals bow.</l>
               <l>'Who haſtes his out with all things neceſſar'e</l>
               <l>'For their intended journey and their fare.</l>
               <l>'But ah! the wicked's mercies cruel are,</l>
               <l>'For they like Bears robb'd of their Whelps when young,</l>
               <l>'With furious haſte after Heav'ns Free-men throng,</l>
               <l>'Reſolving to make one attempt for all,</l>
               <l>'Return Victorious, or for ever fall.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:48379:48"/>'And ſo it was, for they no ſooner
charge</l>
               <l>'The Rear of thoſe he did intend t' inlarge,</l>
               <l>'Than the great Angel of the Covenant came,</l>
               <l>'(As after in the Fleſh) and quencht their flame:</l>
               <l>'He was the guide, who led them to the ſhore,</l>
               <l>'A place made by his power fit to paſs o'er,</l>
               <l>'A Cloud gave light to them that went before.</l>
               <l>'He view'd the Rear, and made the Cloud opac</l>
               <l>'To 'maze th' <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and to keep them back,</l>
               <l>'Commanding <hi>Moſes</hi> to divide the ſtream,</l>
               <l>'While they all night lay in a Golden dream.</l>
               <l>'Pleas'd with the hopes of Conqueſt, while the Sun</l>
               <l>'Show'd them the Neſt, from whence the Birds were gone:</l>
               <l>'The way they thought was pleaſant, ſmooth and plain,</l>
               <l>'Not knowing that that way would them enſhrine,</l>
               <l>'And ſo march boldly till a furious Wind</l>
               <l>'Rais'd by <hi>Jehovah,</hi> did the Walls unbind,</l>
               <l>'That rail'd the path to guide his people ſafe</l>
               <l>'To th' other ſide. This did th' <hi>Egyptians</hi> chafe,</l>
               <l>'For untam'd ſurges ſwell and fill the place,</l>
               <l>'Where <hi>Iſrael</hi> dry-ſhod walkt, no empty ſpace</l>
               <l>'Was left. The Quick-ſands riſe, they ſink below,</l>
               <l>'The billows did their Chariots overthrow,</l>
               <l>'Teaching them by experience Heav'n to know.</l>
               <l>'Half dead, ſome backward and ſome forward ſtrive,</l>
               <l>'Tho <hi>Neptune</hi> vow'd none ſhould go out alive.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:48379:48"/>'Prayers were their laſt ſhift, but they
pray'd in vain,</l>
               <l>'Men of deſerv'd ills muſt not complain.</l>
               <l>'Their King they blame for his ill conduct had,</l>
               <l>'He blames himſelf for all his inſults made</l>
               <l>'Gainſt God and <hi>Iſra'l,</hi> the laſt words he
ſaid.</l>
               <l>'His Standards fallen, and all his daring blades,</l>
               <l>'Drunk with the Sea, he tumbled to the ſhades.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="song">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:48379:49"/>
            <head>THE SONG of <hi>MOSES</hi> After the VICTORY. <hi>EXOD.</hi>
XV.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>'AWake my Soul and ſing <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s praiſe,</l>
               <l>'O! may <hi>Jehovah</hi> my dull Spirits raiſe,</l>
               <l>'May Heav'n's Arch-Flamine give me light and heat,</l>
               <l>'That I with Zeal may on this ſubject treat.</l>
               <l>'O! that I might that double portion have,</l>
               <l>'<hi>Eijah</hi> once to his <hi>Eliſha</hi> gave.</l>
               <l>'May Choires of Angels from the ſacred Throne,</l>
               <l>'Help me to ſing this <hi>Epinicion.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great God! our lives, our all, we owe to thee,</l>
               <l>For thou alone haſt got this Victory,</l>
               <l>By drowning all our en'mies in the Sea.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:48379:49"/>
               <l>Horſes are vain things to be truſted in,</l>
               <l>Char'ots tho Iron, by the Riders ſin,</l>
               <l>Will drown and ſink when Juſtice doth begin.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No battle ever ſo unequal known,</l>
               <l>Never was hoſt ſo eaſily o'erthrown,</l>
               <l>The Winds and Sea this wond'rous work have done.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We, we faint-hearted Foreigners ſtood ſtill,</l>
               <l>(Trembling and ſcolding) tho againſt our will,</l>
               <l>Until we ſaw our en'mies caſe was ill.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then we ſome proſpect had of Victory,</l>
               <l>When thou for us a path made thro the Sea,</l>
               <l>'Twas thou, not we triumphed gloriouſly.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We thro thy ſtrength do ſtand upon this ſhore,</l>
               <l>And ſee our en'mies floating dead, nay, more,</l>
               <l>Their Horſe and Chariots toſt the flood all o're.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is my ſtrength, my ſong, and my ſalvation,</l>
               <l>He hath reliev'd the hated <hi>Hebrew</hi> Nation,</l>
               <l>Therefore I will build him an habitation.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Covenant with faithful <hi>Abra'm</hi> made,</l>
               <l>What he to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and to <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid,</l>
               <l>Is all fulfilled by this our preſent aid.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:48379:50"/>
               <l>What Men of War do for thoſe in diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>His pow'r for (feeble) us hath done no leſs,</l>
               <l>His name's <hi>Jehovah</hi> whom we'll ever bleſs.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The proud Kings Hoſt was utterly deſtroy'd,</l>
               <l>When they our Lives and Land thought to've enjoy'd,</l>
               <l>And us (as formerly) in Bricks employ'd.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His choſen men not able to withſtand,</l>
               <l>The watry Troops unhors'd, and on the Land</l>
               <l>Are caſt or bury'd in the ſlimy Sand.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This unknown way was made for us alone,</l>
               <l>Soft for our feet, the Rocks upon us ſhone,</l>
               <l>Which they attempting, ſunk down like a Stone.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We have exper'ence of thy wondrous pow'r,</l>
               <l>Thy glor'ous right hand did our foes devour,</l>
               <l>Saving us at our laſt and fatal hour.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou didſt but blow upon them, yet that wind</l>
               <l>Gather'd the floods together, and did bind</l>
               <l>Them up in heaps, that we a way might find.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:48379:50"/>
               <l>The en'my ſaid, purſuing we will take</l>
               <l>Theſe fugitives, and kill or bring them back,</l>
               <l>Dividing all the ſpoil we from them take.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lord! who among the Gods is like to thee?</l>
               <l>Spotleſs and Holy, full of Majeſty,</l>
               <l>Thy praiſes fearful, wonders many be.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy mercy we believe will ſave and lead</l>
               <l>Thy Sons redeem'd unto a fertile meed,</l>
               <l>Where they may ſafely reſt and freely feed.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They that inhabit <hi>Paleſtine</hi> ſhall hear,</l>
               <l>Approaching ſorrow will increaſe their fear,</l>
               <l>With all their Neigbouring Countries far or near.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The lofty Dukes of <hi>Edom</hi> ſhall be then</l>
               <l>Greatly amazed, <hi>Moab</hi>'s mighty men</l>
               <l>Loſing their courage, tremble ſhall with pain.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Canaanites</hi> (tho ſtrong) with grief oppreſt,</l>
               <l>With trembling hearts and voice will ſay, it's beſt</l>
               <l>To leave the Land, that <hi>Iſra'l</hi> may have reſt.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such dread ſhall fall upon them by thine arm,</l>
               <l>As will their mouths ſtop, leſt they offer harm</l>
               <l>To us when we do over <hi>Jordan</hi> ſwarm.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:48379:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Then to the place of thy great holineſs</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt us bring, and we with joy expreſs</l>
               <l>In all our Songs this weighty buſineſs.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Say'ng, O Lord, thou ſhalt for ever reign,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, who caus'd our pain</l>
               <l>Are drown'd, and we on dry Land ſee them ſlain.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is our turn, ſaid <hi>Miriam</hi> now to ſing,</l>
               <l>The weaker Sex by praiſe may honour bring</l>
               <l>Unto <hi>Jehovah Niſſi,</hi> our great King.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our inſtruments of all ſorts let us take</l>
               <l>Harps, Flutes, with Timbrels and ſweet Muſic make</l>
               <l>To him, who hath wrought wonders for our ſake.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great God! our lives, our all we owe to thee,</l>
               <l>Since thou alone haſt wrought this Victory,</l>
               <l>By drowning all our enemies in the Sea.</l>
               <l>Sing <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48379:51"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
